<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Catholick mirrour. Or, a looking-glasse for Protestants Wherein they may plainly see the errours of their church, and the truth of the Roman Catholick. Which is divided into seventeen chapters, containing the principle points in dispute between Catholicks and Protestants, and all proved by their own Bible, for the satisfaction of those that desire to imbrace true religion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1494A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895301</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895301</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152613</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152613)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2309:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Catholick mirrour. Or, a looking-glasse for Protestants Wherein they may plainly see the errours of their church, and the truth of the Roman Catholick. Which is divided into seventeen chapters, containing the principle points in dispute between Catholicks and Protestants, and all proved by their own Bible, for the satisfaction of those that desire to imbrace true religion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 147, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152613:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152613:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>AMongſt all the Miſeries that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our Humane Frailty, there is none to be ſo much bewailed, as the ſtupidity of our mindes, which renders us worſe then beaſts, and deprives us of that felicity for which we were Created, which was to fill up the glorious places of the Lapſed Angels, and ſo have been happy to all eternity: the verity of this will plainly appear, when we conſider the madneſs of this our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, where People ſuck in Errour, as Children do Milk from their Mothers Breaſts; and unadviſedly repel Truth, as one would do a Serpent that attempts their ruine; they hiſs at thoſe that invites them to Happineſs, and hug the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their Miſery, that imbrace all kindes of Novelties, and kick againſt
<pb facs="tcp:152613:2"/>ancient verities; that cry out the Bible, the Bible, and yet believe nothing in it, more then their own Fancies dictate to them: Now that theſe people (of which there is too many) may a little ſee, and know their own Errours, I ſhall in this following Diſcourſe, prove that their own Bibles, which they pretend to confide in, both is, and ſhall be, their aſſured Judge, to condemn their erroneous opinions, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their guide (being rightly underſtood) to the knowledge of the Truth; as alſo make it appear, that all the chief points of Religion, which Proteſtants deny, and Roman Catholicks practice, is found and commanded in their own Bibles; by which will appear with what partial eyes they have looked upon Scripture, that read it over ſo often, and cannot ſee thoſe places which pointeth Gods Church, and the Faith thereof ſo plainly to them; for it is indeed with theſe kinde of people as it is with the Jews to this day, who though they read in the Old Teſtament the Prophecies which plainly foretold Chriſts coming, his Life, and dolorous Death, yet are ſo blinded with unbelief, that they cannot underſtand the ſame; ſo all that
<pb facs="tcp:152613:2"/>are now out of Gods Church, read and tumble over the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet cannot ſee the plain places, which all Chriſtians are bound to believe, under the peril of damnation; and all this is, becauſe men have preſumptuous mindes in truſting to their own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and will not relye on Gods Church, which plainly ſhews them to her Members, when none elſe can, becauſe ſhe onely is guided in all truth, by the Holy Ghoſt, to the end of the world. All there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I ſhall deſire of every Proteſtant Reader, is onely this, that he minde and look cloſely to every Text of Scripture here quoted, and what is ſaid, with an impartial eye, and obſerve well how Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and reaſon concur in the truth of what is treated of, concerning our Faith (which is ſo much ſlandered by their teachers and others) for though it be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made on by ſome, yet they ſhall one day finde, that the diligent ſearch after truth was one of the main things for which we were ſent into the world: which truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing practiſed in Gods Church, is here plainly proved; which though not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately dreſſed with crafty Sentences, but
<pb facs="tcp:152613:3"/>in poor and ſimple ſtyle, may I hope pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the deſired effects, for which it was intended; that is, that all deceived people may finde the way to Gods Church, that all Ignorance and Errours may be baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Truth take place; that true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may flouriſh, as a green Bay-Tree, and Hereſies and Factions wither as Plants without rain; that living all our lives in communion with Gods Church, we may at laſt enjoy that bleſſed end, for which we were created.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152613:3"/>
            <head>THE Catholick Mirrour.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> This is to prove the Verity of the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Body and Blood of our Saviour, and that it is really ſo, contrary to Proteſtants Opinion.</head>
               <p>THe Misbelief of theſe times is ſuch, that it may give a juſt aſtoniſhment to all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; eſpecially when they conſider how little Faith many have in this moſt Bleſſed Sacrament: and that there is no one thing our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did ſo much inculcate to us (in his whole life) concerning any point of Faith as this; he very well knowing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152613:4"/>the greatneſs of the Myſtery, and the ſmallneſs of our Faith: it is in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture often mentioned to be really his Body and Blood, becauſe we may plead no excuſe by any miſtake of one place alone; and firſt you ſhall ſee how this Bleſſed Sacrament was prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured to us in the Old Teſtament, by the holy men of God, and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as in <hi>Exodus</hi> 16.15. concerning the Manna which came down from Heaven to the Iſraelites to feed their Bodies; ſo that foretold of this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Manna which feeds our Souls: for ſhould not this Bleſſed Sacrament be of greater value then Proteſtants make of it, who ſay it is barely Bread, and a Figure onely of Chriſt his Body, then this Manna, which was indeed a Figure, would be of greater validity then that which it prefigured, which is very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to think. A ſecond Figure we finde in Scripture, is that Holy Bread of Propoſition,<note place="margin">Exod. 25 &amp; Lev. 24. v. 5.6, 7.</note> or Shew-Bread; which becauſe it was a Figure of this moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, was to be made and eaten with ſuch purity, that none but ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons was to eat of it; to ſhew
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152613:4"/>with what purity and reverence we ought to approach theſe Holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The third Figure in Holy Writ is the Paſchal Lamb,<note place="margin">Exod. 12. v. 3.4, 5, 6, &amp;c.</note> an eminent Figure of this Sacrament; wherein you may obſerve what Ceremonies God exacted from the Jews in the eating of it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though but a Type of this: from whence we may gather, that this which Chriſt hath Inſtituted is to be had in a far higher eſteem amongſt Chriſtians, as requiring greater Faith in the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it, and reverence in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. The fourth Figure was the Ark,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.10.11, 12.</note> whereof the Holy Doctor Saint <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1.2. q. 102. ar.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That even as the Ark was made of the Wood of <hi>Sethim,</hi> that is, of pure and ſhining Cedar; even ſo the Body of our Lord conſiſteth of moſt pure Members. Again, the Ark was gilded both within and without, the which gilding ſignifieth the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Charity of Chriſt our Lord. In the Ark were three things. 1. There was a golden Pot, wherein was kept Manna, and was a figure of the Soul of Chriſt, which containeth all plenitude of Sanctity and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152613:5"/>2. There was the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which ſignified the Prieſtly Power of Chriſt; and as the Ark ſtood in the Tabernacle covered with a Vail, even ſo Chriſt lyeth hidden in this Divine Sacrament, under the Forms and Accidents of Bread and Wine, which we muſt diſcover with the eyes of Divine Faith, according to Saint <hi>Paul, That Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> 3. There was in the Arke the two tables of Stone, to ſignifie that Chriſt ſhould be a Law-giver; and this being one of his greateſt Laws, to believe in him, let us take him at his word, and thank him for ſo great a good, as is this pure Sacrament of his Body and Blood.</q> I ſhall now begin to forſake the Shadows, and let the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of our happineſs appear, in clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proving by the Holy Word of God, that we now injoy in reality what they did but prefigure to us. And firſt from the words of Chriſt himſelf, by Saint <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. v. 26.27, 28.</note> where he ſaith in private to his twelve Diſciples onely; <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body, and drink ye
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152613:5"/>all of it, for this is my Blood;</hi> he names here no Figures, but in plain tearms, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and had not our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour meant what he here ſaid, he would have expounded his words, both for the benefit of his Apoſtles, and all us beſides, who have no better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in any thing (for our ſalvation) then his word, which is truth it ſelf. The ſecond Text is from Saint <hi>Marks</hi> Goſpel, where he ſaith, Chriſt <hi>took bread and bleſt it, and ſaid, Take, eat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 14. v. 22. 23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>this is my body, which ſhall be given for you;</hi> and ſo of the Cup, he ſaid to them, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament which ſhall be ſhed for you;</hi> now I leave it to all reaſonable Chriſtians (that are not partial to their own Souls) to conſider, whether Chriſt did onely in Figure give his Body to dye for us, and his Blood in Figure to be ſhed, or his real Body and Blood; if he gave them really for us to death, he ſaith here, that this is that Body, and that ſame Blood in this Sacrament; ſo that to deny this, is to give our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour the flat lye; and in refuſing of Chriſts words here, may as well ſhake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152613:6"/>hands, and bid adieu to all points o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian Faith; for that Saint <hi>James</hi> his Apoſtle ſaith, That he which break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one Commandment is guilty of all, meaning, in the not believing of one, he may as well not believe any. Our Saviour to confirm to us, what he told us by the two precedent Apoſtles, hath inſpired Saint <hi>Luke</hi> to publiſh this great myſtery,<note place="margin">Luke 22. v. 19, 20.</note> where in the Text you may finde the ſame words recited, as was before by Saint <hi>Mark;</hi> but above all, you ſhall finde the beloved Diſciple more ample in declaring the words of his Maſter,<note place="margin">John 6. v. 50, 51, 52, &amp;c.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>That the bread which I will give is my fleſh, which I will give for the life of the world:</hi> now the Jews wanting faith (as too many now adayes do) ſaid, as Hereticks now do, <hi>How can this man give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> not underſtanding what manner Chriſt meant to beſtow it on us. Our Saviour who came into the world to lead us into all truth, would have open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed undoubtedly his meaning to them, if he had had any other; but he was ſo far from ſhewing any other meaning of his words, that he reiterates them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152613:6"/>over and over again, ſaying, <hi>Except you eat the Fleſh of the Son of man and drink his Blood, ye have no life in you;</hi> and ſo proceeds in the confirmation of what he ſaid before: and which is very remarkable, his Diſciples which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and had frequently heard his Doctrine could not comprehend how this great myſtery ſhould be brought to paſs; ſo diſtruſting his Godhead,<note place="margin">Ver. 60, 61.</note> (wherein his power lay to accompliſh it) <hi>They went away</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and walked no more with him.</hi> By which every Chriſtian may eaſily underſtand, that if our Saviour had not meant what he ſaid concerning this Sacrament, he would not have ſuffered his Diſciples which he loved ſo well, to have gone away and left him; but would have then, as he did at other times when he ſpake parables, expounded the meaning: but you ſee he had no other meaning, for he ſweetly complains to the others, and <hi>will ye alſo go away;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 67.</note> but St. <hi>Peter</hi> anſwers for them that ſtayed, <hi>To whom ſhall we go,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 68.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt the words of eternal life:</hi> ſo that we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that they believing in his words,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152613:7"/>ſtayed behinde with him, and would, not leave our Saviour as the reſt did; therefore it concerns every Chriſtian, as they tender their ſalvation, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what hath been ſaid by our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour concerning this grand My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Chriſtian Religion, and not any more to queſtion Chriſts meaning: for ſince we know, he hath often ſaid, it is his Body and Blood, and we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe know that it was in his power to make the Bread and Wine ſo, by his Divine Benediction: there remains nothing for us to doubt, but to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Spirits, in ſubmitting to our Bleſſed Saviours Doctrine, and to ſay as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did, <hi>Lord, thou haſt the words of eternal life.</hi> And that you may in this great point of Faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive further ſatisfaction, I ſhall reduce to your memory the opinion of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who you ſhall ſee verifies what hath been ſaid before; for faith he, <hi>The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. v. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt; and the Bread of bleſſing which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt:</hi> he names no Figures here, nor
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152613:7"/>fancies of we know not what, but of Communion of Chriſts ſacred Body and Blood: who came into the world to aboliſh all Figures, and out of his immenſe goodneſs to leave us his divine ſelf for the conſolation of our ſouls. And for our further aſſurance, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his next Chapter treateth more amply and telleth the manner of the inſtitution,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. v. 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> as you may read in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cited in his Epiſtle, where likewiſe he ſaith, That by frequent partaking of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, we ſhew forth the Lords death. Perhaps ſome will anſwer, it is meant for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Death; and of them I would demand, what better memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial can there be of any perſon, then to have the ſaid perſon preſent: for example, when our Saviour appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> and ſhewed him his ſacred wounds, then he remembred him, and cryed, <hi>Thou art my Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 20. v. 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and my God?</hi> and ſo it is frequently amongſt friends, that hath been long abſent, that are forgot one by another, till frequent converſation reduces to their memory the knowledge of each
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152613:8"/>other, and do commonly ſay in ſuch caſes, O! now I remember you. So by frequent Communion with Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament, we have the beſt memorial his goodneſs could leave unto us. Again, he ſaith, <hi>That whoſoever eateth and drinketh</hi> theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries <hi>unworthily, eateth and drinketh his own damnation, not diſcerning the Lords Body;</hi> ſo that by theſe words it is plain, there is a Body to be diſcerned by the eyes of our Faith; and as plain, that damnation would not follow by eating bare bread and Wine. From theſe ſo evident places of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, I hope every good Chriſtian will be induced to the belief of this great Sacrament, and no more queſtion the works of God, but conclude with that holy man, <hi>Thomas de Kempes,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That if the wonderful works of God were to be underſtood by our reaſon, they could not be ſaid to be wonderful and unſpeakable.</q> Thus have I ſhewed the truth of this Sacrament by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants own Bible, which though it work not my deſired effects in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of it, yet I hope it will reduce them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152613:8"/>to a more charitable opinion of us, who think our ſelves bound to believe it, becauſe it is inſerted in Holy Scripture; according to that of our Saviour, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for therein you ſhall finde eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Proving Sacramental Confeſſion, both by Holy Scripture, and Reaſon; againſt the Opinion of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>HAd we the prudence of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, in ſubmitting our Judgements to Gods Church, both as concerning this verity, and all others; we ſhould not have ſo much peeviſh wrangling continually as we have, in points of Faith; but contrariwiſe we ſhould joyn hand in hand in one uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Doctrine of Chriſtian Religion: but being far from that happineſs, in this age we are poſſeſt with quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for every one will be his own Judge, and paſs ſentence, though it be againſt Scripture and Reaſont too: and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152613:9"/>this will plainly appear, when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Confeſſion hath been the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all Ages ſince Chriſt to this day. I ſhall not need to produce the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of every Age, (which might eaſily be done) it being out of my deſign; becauſe it is ſo plainly commanded in Holy Writ, which ought not by any that profeſſeth himſelf a Chriſtian to be denied: and if not ſo, of neceſſity to be put in practice. The firſt place I ſhall prove it from, is out of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Saint <hi>Matthew;</hi> who ſpeaking of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm,<note place="margin">Mat. 3. v. 5.6.</note> ſaith, <hi>They came from Jeruſalem, and Judea, and were Baptized of him, confeſſing their Sins.</hi> Now to evade this Text, the Proteſtants ſay, That the people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed themſelves in general to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But how poor this ſhift is, let every one judge, that hath a minde to know the truth; for St. <hi>John</hi> knew, and we all know, that every man in general is a ſinner without their ſaying ſo; but the Text ſaith, <hi>They confeſſed their ſins:</hi> which plainly argueth every ones parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſins. Again, you ſhall ſee what another Evangeliſt ſaith to the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152613:9"/>purpoſe;<note place="margin">Mark 1. v. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>And there went out to him all the land of Judea, and they of Jeruſalem, and were all baptized of him in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Jordan, confeſſing their ſins.</hi> It may juſtly bring an aſToniſhment on the ſouls of true Chriſtians, to conſider that thoſe people which ſay they will believe nothing but the Bible, yet when they come to the touchſtone of it, will believe never a word more then what their own fancies pleaſe. But now as I have ſhown you how this was practiſed amongſt the Jews in our Saviours time, ſo now you ſhall be ſhown how Chriſts Apoſtle, from him, doth command the ſame. Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">James 5. v. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Confeſs your ſins one to another;</hi> and in all reaſon and duty, ſince it is thus commanded, we are bound under the penalty of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to do all the commands of the New Teſtament, at leaſt, to believe them to be lawful. Many examples of this practice have we in the Old Teſtament commanded by God himſelf, as in <hi>Numbers,</hi> he ſaith,<note place="margin">Numb. 5. v. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>That if any man or woman had committed any ſins, that then they ſhall confeſs their ſin, and he ſhall recompence his treſpaſs committed.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152613:10"/>So <hi>David</hi> uſed Confeſſion to <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. v. 13.</note> and if there were no Scripture at all, Reaſon might tell us, that it is a Divine Inſtitution: Firſt, in regard of the goodneſs that is in it ſelf; for we finde nothing more repugnant to our corrupt natures, then to confeſs our ſins to a Prieſt: from which we may gather, that the more it is againſt our frail natures, the more it hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Gods will; in regard, by ſad experience we all finde, how difficult it is for us to comply with Gods will, in thoſe things that concerns our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, The thought of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our ſins to a Prieſt oftentimes hinders our deſign, in committing ſins. Thirdly, by confeſſing our ſins to a Prieſt (to whom God hath given our ſouls in charge,<note place="margin">Heb. 13. v. 17.</note> and muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for them) he knows what ſins we are infected with, and knows the better what Doctrine to preach to us, for the remedy of our ſpiritual diſtempers: And can any reaſonable man think, that if it were not a Divine Law, that ſo many Emperours, and Kings, and Princes as are, and have been, would
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152613:10"/>ſtoop on their knees to a poor Prieſt in a gray courſe Gown, to make their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion? No, we may well imagine they would not (being men that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow the dictates of their own will) did not their conſciences tell them it was from God, and not of mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. Now by this you may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee what reaſon the Catholick Church hath to propoſe Confeſſion to her Children; and likewiſe what mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs 'tis for Proteſtants and others to impugne ſo naked a Truth, and ſo good a principle of Faith as Confeſſion is. My advice therefore is to all, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy not this benefit, That they would beſeech the giver of all goodneſs, to unite them in communion with his holy Catholick Church, and make them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Members thereof, if they expect ſalvation from his hands; according to that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That he that will not acknowledge the Church for his Mother, cannot lawfully call God his Father: and that out of the Catholic Church there is no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152613:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Proving Purgatory, or a temporal ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to Gods Juſtice for our ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted here, againſt the Belief of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</head>
               <p>DId we not by the irregular paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our mindes throw down Reaſon, the Queen of our ſouls, and ſet up an Idol in her place, called Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhould with much facility im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this verity ſo long practiſed by Gods Church; though it were for no other reaſon, but becauſe it is practiſed there: but ſince nothing but Scripture will ſerve the turns of many in the world, I ſhall plainly ſet it forth by that rule, that they may have no excuſe to deceive themſelves: But firſt it is neceſſary to let you know, that as God hath theſe two Attributes, (to wit) Mercy and Juſtice; ſo he is to have them both ſatisfied. As to the firſt he ſatisfies himſelf in pouring down his Spiritual and Temporal Bleſſings into our Souls and Bodies, for the good of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152613:11"/>both. And the ſecond muſt be ſatisfied, either in our doing or ſuffering accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as our ſins deſerve. Agreeable to this truth is that ſatisfaction which God hath required in Scripture ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: for example,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> that of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; for ſo ſoon as they had abuſed the mercy of God, which placed them there, preſently his Juſtice expected ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by repelling them from thence; and yet for that ſin, many thouſands have, and ſhall be damned: and for the ſins of the world, we know Gods Juſtice was ſo urgent for ſatisfaction, that he drowned the whole world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe in the Ark: he ſatisfied his Juſtice alſo many times in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Iſraelites in the deſert; and for the ſins of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> we all know what ſatisfaction God gave to his Juſtice,<note place="margin">Num. 16. v. 31.32.</note> when he cauſed the earth to open and ſwallow them up alive. Now is it not ſtrange to think how little reaſon we have to flatter our ſelves as we do, and think we ſhall get to heaven in a dream, without any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction on our part at all. If we did but truly conſider our own ſtate, we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152613:12"/>ſhould not have ſo good an opinion of our ſelves as to think God ſhould pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſo many to ſatisfie his Juſtice, and we ſhould ſcape ſcot-free: Nay, thoſe whom he dearly loved, as <hi>Moſes</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving him of entrance into the land of Promiſe.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. ver. 10.</note> But more to our purpoſe is that of holy <hi>David,</hi> where for his ſin with <hi>Bathſaba,</hi> God told him the Sword ſhould never depart from his houſe. Now here <hi>Davids</hi> ſin was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned (as to the eternal puniſhment) but yet Gods juſtice requiring from him this temporal ſatisfaction, as the ſword cleaving to his houſe, and the death of of his Childe.<note place="margin">Ver. 14.</note> A plainer place cannot be to prove what is here treated of, and I hope it is good Scripture: But to let you ſee further, that you may be totally undeceived, conform to this place, is another concerning the ſame man; where for his ſin in numbring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24. ver. 14.15, 16, &amp;c.</note> though God told him (by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Gad</hi>) he had pardoned him his ſin; yet he to ſatisfie his Juſtice cauſed his Angel to deſtroy ſeventy thouſand of them, which to <hi>Davids</hi> heart was a hot Purgatory, or temporal puniſhment.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152613:12"/>Thus you ſee many times God hath been pleaſed to be ſo favourable to ſome of his deareſt friends to purge them here (by the fire of tribulations) as <hi>Adam, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> with many others which might be ſhown; but this to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men will ſuffice, ſince it is ſo plain by the holy word of God And now it will concern me to ſhew you (by the fame word) that there is a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment, or Purgatory after death: I will onely give you this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it before I quote my Text, which is, that ſince there be many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God which dye unpuniſhed here in this life, for their ſins commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo have not ſatisfied Gods Juſtice, muſt of neceſſity do it, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purified before they can go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for the Scripture ſaith plainly, that no unclean thing can enter in there; and if ſo, we may eaſily judge, how unclean thouſands are which dye Chriſtians, and in communion with Gods Church, but yet not jump juſt to heaven, but are purged by fire.</p>
               <p>And to ſatisfie you in this, you muſt obſerve what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152613:13"/>Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. v. 12.13.</note> where firſt he tells us the different ſorts of works, by the ſimilitudes of Gold, Silver, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, Wood, Hay, Stubble, and then how this fire ſhall try them; for ſaith he, <hi>Every mans works ſhall be made manifeſt, and the day (of our Lord) ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fire, and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is.</hi> Again, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Ver. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>If any mans work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs, but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo, as by fire;</hi> by which it is plain, that we muſt paſs through this fiery tryal (before we get to heaven) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by great croſſes here in this life, or elſe in the purging place of the life to come. It would be worth our time, did we but ſeriouſly conſider, how that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons which have been the dearly beloved friends of Chriſt have had in this life the greateſt ſhare of temporal puniſhment, as his ever Bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (though I will not ſay for her ſins) the twelve Apoſtles, and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Martyrs, which have ſatisfied Gods Juſtice, with the loſs of their blood; and yet we now adayes hug
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152613:13"/>our ſelves in a ſottiſh ſecurity, and think we ſhall be conveyed to heaven in Beds of Roſes; as if God were ſo partial to mankinde to puniſh thoſe that were good and holy, and ſpare us that have much more deſerved it. But now again to the Scripture, to let you ſee what our Saviour ſaith, concerning paying our debts to God, and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins in the next life; as in Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> he ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 5. v. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>We ſhould be at agreement with our adverſary, leſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us over to the Judge, and the Judge throw us into priſon, from whence we ſhall not get out, till we have paid the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing.</hi> Now in reſpect of our ſins, God is our adverſary, and if we agree not with him here; that is, to ſatisfie his juſtice by Alms-deeds, tears, and ſuffering in this life, he will throw us into the priſon of Purgatory, till we have ſatisfied the debt there. Again, ſaith our Saviour,<note place="margin">Mat. 12. v. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoever ſpeaketh againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall never be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in this life, nor in the world to come;</hi> by which it is plain, that as Gods juſtice is ſatisfied here by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſins, ſo there is ſins to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152613:14"/>in the life to come, which muſt be in Purgatory; for out of Hell is no redemption, nor no expectation of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſins. Did there not want a right underſtanding in the hearts of men concerning Scripture, there could not be ſo much errour and blindeneſs in the reading of it as there is, for all thoſe places which plainly ſhow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and the Catholique Faith, are paſt by, and no more minded then if they had no relation to Gods word at all. If moſt Proteſtants that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to read this book, ſhould but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their own conſciences, they could not but confeſs that moſt places here cited (to prove our faith) was ſo little taken notice of, that they knew not whether they were in the Bible or no: And now after all theſe Texts here mentioned out of holy Writ to prove this point, if any Proteſtant will or can ſhew me but one place in all the Bible, that any one went, or was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to Heaven, as ſoon as they dyed, I do aſſure them I will (as once I was) be of their Faith; but if they cannot, then are they obliged in conſcience to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152613:14"/>believe what is ſaid, or be guilty of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity to God and his Holy Word: and to the intent that I may plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the errour of thoſe that believe there is, nor before Chriſts coming was, any other places then Heaven and Hell after death; it is my purpoſe therefore in the next Chapter to prove that there is a third place wherein the Fathers of the New Teſtament were, which could not obtain Heaven till Chriſt had ſhed his Blood for them; according to that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of the Faith of thoſe holy men; yet he ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11. v. 39.40.</note> 
                  <hi>All theſe having obtained a good report, by faith, received not the promiſe (which was Heaven) God having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect.</hi> But the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon objection and deceit againſt this, which takes ſo much is, that Chriſt hath ſatisfied Gods Juſtice for our ſins, what need we do any thing at all; and this is the uſuall juggle of thoſe that teach againſt this point of ſatisfaction; but we are to conſider how far Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction extends to us, that is, he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the pardon of our original ſins,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152613:15"/>and not for our actual tranſgreſſions, (though they be the eaſier pardoned by the merits of his Death too) for if all our actual ſins were pardoned and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for, by the Death of Chriſt, why then all Heathens, and Turks, and Whoremongers, and Murderers, and Blaſphemers ſhould be ſaved; which, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Shall never enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> ſo that this is but a trick of our Adverſaries ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the people believe that they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all to Chriſt, when indeed, if juſtly conſidered, they load his ſhoulders with their actual ſins, that hath ſuffered enough already for our original ones; and ſo they would fain free themſelves from all kinde of ſufferings, here and hereafter; when our Saviour ſaith, <hi>We cannot enter into life eternal without much tribulation:</hi> but as I ſaid, God is merciful to ſave, ſo he is juſt to puniſh; and it is not good for us to preſume too much upon hhis mercy, leſt we fall into a provocation of his Juſtice, and ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh everlaſtingly. And ſince it is ſo plain both by holy Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that there is a purging place, or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152613:15"/>temporal puniſhments in the life to come (proportionable to every ones ſins) let every man conſider what obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation he hath, firſt, to believe it to be ſo; ſecondly, to live ſo holily in this life, that God may be pleaſed to ſpare us, by extenuating our ſufferings in thoſe purifying flames, agreeable to that of B. St. <hi>Bernard;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. <hi>6.</hi> tribulat. in fine.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Oh would to God ſome man would now before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand provide for my head abundance of water, and to mine eyes a fountain of tears; for ſo haply the burning fire ſhould take no hold, where run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tears had cleanſed before.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Proving that none of the Holy Fathers of the Old Law enjoyed Heaven till Chriſt came, and that there was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct place where they waited for their Redemption by his coming.</head>
               <p>REaſon doth tell us, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will juſtifie the ſame, that all the glorious and ſplendid things of this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152613:16"/>world are obtained with much difficulty and travel, ſo that ſcarce the tythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of men have the fruition of them: and is it not to be lamented, that we have ſo poor and beggerly apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of heavenly glory, as to think it requires no difficulty, no patience, nor no ſuffering to obtain that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; the contrary will plainly appear when I ſhall prove by Scripture, that no ſoul from <hi>Adam</hi> till Chriſt dyed, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed heavenly Glory, but ſuffered with long patience and expectation, till they were redeemed by the precious Blood of our Saviour, and ſo freed from their long captivity; conformable to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who writing of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. v. 8.9.</note> ſaith, <hi>When he aſcended up on high, he led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men.</hi> And again, <hi>Now that he aſcended, what is it, but that he deſcended firſt into the lower parts of the earth.</hi> Now I would from theſe words have every Proteſtant conſider theſe two things: Firſt, to what place Chriſt deſcended after his Death, and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who they were that he led with him captive at his aſcenſion from that place.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152613:16"/>It is clear to all Chriſtians that Chriſt did not deſcend to the Hell of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to releaſe them from any captivity; for as I ſaid before, there is no redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption for them: what other thing can be concluded, but that he went to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe them which could not be ſaved till then, for is it not madneſs to think that any people went to Heaven before Chriſt had redeemed them with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood: next you ſhall ſee what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith concerning this point;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. Ver. 18. Ver. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the Fleſh, but quickned by the Spirit: by which alſo he went and preacht unto the ſpirits in priſon.</hi> Now what can be deſired more plain then this, ſhowing ſo plainly, that when Chriſts fleſh lay dead, his ſpirit preacht to thoſe that were long in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting of him in a priſon, to them that ſighed ſo long for his coming: the ſame did the Prophet <hi>Zachariah</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, where ſpeaking to <hi>Sion, Behold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 9. ver. 9.</note> ſaith he, <hi>thy King cometh, he is juſt, and having ſalvation, lowly, and riding upon an Aſs, and upon a Colt, the foal of an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152613:17"/>Aſs:</hi> here he ſpeaks of Chriſts coming; and in the other verſe,<note place="margin">Ver. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>As for thee alſo by the blood of thy Covenant, I have ſent forth thy priſoners out of the pit wherein was no water:</hi> Now what pit can this be imagined to be, but this place where theſe holy men were, in which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, that Chriſt at his coming to <hi>Sion</hi> would deliver them out; and if we conſider this point as we ought to do, we ſhall finde it to be an Article of our Creed;<note place="margin">Article 4. of our Creed.</note> which ſaith, <hi>He deſcended into Hell, the third day he roſe again:</hi> Now ſome object, by this Hell is meant the grave, but how abſurdly let every one judge, that conſiders how ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous it is to think Chriſts ſoul ſhould remain in the Grave; his Body we grant did ſo, but his glorious Spirit went to perform what before had been ſaid of him, according to his own moſt bleſſed words, when he ſaid, <hi>That as Jonas was three dayes and three nights in the belly of the whale, ſo ſhall the Son of man be three dayes and three nights in the heart of the earth:</hi> ſo his body, as I ſaid, was in the Grave, and his Soul in the other place, which is commonly called Hell,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152613:17"/>(becauſe it is believed to be under the earth as the Hell of the damned is.) Now this place may ſuffice to any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Chriſtian, yet I ſhall propoſe one or two things more to your conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, as firſt concerning <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 11. v. 42, 43.</note> who was dead and buried four dayes, and was raiſed to life by our Saviour: I hope none will ſay he was in Hell with the damned; and had he been in Heaven, you may be ſure his Siſters had a better ſenſe of that Glory, then to wiſh him upon earth again; and if he had been in either place, we know there is no coming out, as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Luke 16. v. 26.</note> ſpeaking of <hi>Dives</hi> and the other <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> ſo that we muſt conclude his ſoul to be in that temporal Hell, ſpoken of in our Creed, or no where at all: and Holy <hi>David</hi> cryes out to God, ſaying, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in Hell, for Lord thou loveſt me,</hi> &amp;c. Now this may be objected two wayes againſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: Firſt (that if it meant the Grave) what ſhould his ſoul do to be left there: And ſecondly, if it means that temporall Hell (as undoubtedly it doth) then it plainly ſhows that his ſoul
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152613:18"/>was there, becauſe it ſaith, <hi>Thou wilt not leave it in Hell:</hi> We may gather much to our preſent purpoſe from the laſt Text mentioned in Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> where <hi>Dives</hi> being <hi>in Hell lift up his eyes and ſaw Abraham afar off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus in his boſom,</hi> which plainly proves <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> not to be in Heaven; for could the damned in Hell ſee the Saints in Heaven, it would be no Hell to them, ſince the ſight of Heaven is ſo glorious, it would take away the ſenſe of Hell, and ſo make them happy in that unhappy place. Again, if <hi>Abraham</hi> had been in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, according to Proteſtants opinion, they could not hear one the other ſpeak, being at that vaſt diſtance as Heaven and Hell is; for they ſay how can the Saints hear our prayers on earth, much leſs (if not ſo) could they hear them in Hell. We may again ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the place where <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Fathers were, was not far from the local Hell of the damned, but (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, The upper part, or over it ſome diſtance; where holy <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">ver. 26.</note> there was a gulf that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152613:18"/>ſeparated the paſſage one to the other, becauſe they could both ſee and ſpeak one to the other. And thus, having made it ſo manifeſtly appear I hope none that profeſſes the truth of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will now any more defile their ſouls with envy to the holy Catholick Church, which teacheth all truth, and nothing but the truth (if you had but as right an underſtanding of all that is there taught as you have of this) but be rather induced to the practice of it, and with Saint <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> to conclude, <q rend="margQuotes">Who is there but an Infidel,<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>99.</hi> Ep. in prin.</note> will deny that Chriſt was in (this temporal) Hell.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Proving that Angels, and Saints in Heaven, do know what paſſeth here on Earth; and ſo conſequently may be prayed to by us, for their mediation to God in our behalf.</head>
               <p>THe mindes of men, being natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined to ſearch, and know
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152613:19"/>the nature of hidden things, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes take indirect wayes to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the knowledge of them, and yet come ſhort in their deſigns too: This thing as it was the ſin of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſo is it a great corruption in this preſent age, amongſt many thouſands, which would make us believe they know on earth, what power and happineſs the Bleſſed Angels and Saints have in heaven, and will grant them no more priviledge then what their ſhallow brains can comprehend they have; quite contrary to that ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. ver. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear hath not heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man, the things that God hath prepared for them that love him:</hi> ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely out of our underſtanding are the qualities of glorified ſouls, which Angels and Saints are. But to let thoſe people know how much they deceive themſelves in foſtering ſuch pernicious opinions, I will prove both by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and Reaſon that they do know all our actions here on earth, and that it is agreeable to the nature of Angels to know them; my firſt place is from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152613:19"/>Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luke 2. ver. 13.</note> where ſo ſoon as our Saviour was born on earth, the Angels came from heaven to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards to anounce it to them, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with great joy; a little before, one in particular told them,<note place="margin">ver. 10.</note> that he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them great joy, for a Saviour was born to them; by which it is plain, that the Angel knew when he was in heaven, that he was born: ſo likewiſe our Saviour when he was in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after his temptation, the Text ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 4. ver. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>The Angels came and miniſtred unto him;</hi> by which you may ſee how ready thoſe bleſſed Spirits are in all things and occaſions to aſſiſt in our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Again, when our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was in his direful Agony in the Garden, ſweating drops of Blood for us, Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Luke 22. ver. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>There appeared an Angel to him from heaven, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him;</hi> from which words we may gather, 1. That if Angels lent their aſſiſtance to ſtrengthen Chriſt, who is the God of ſtrength, much more will they to us (by Gods permiſſion) who are of our ſelves nothing but weakneſs. 2. That if they knew not what paſſeth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152613:20"/>on earth, how could they ſo readily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt us, as we read in many places of the Bible they have done, and as I ſhall prove hereafter: Our Saviour ſaith likewiſe by the ſame Evangeliſt,<note place="margin">Luke 15. ver. 13.</note> That there is joy in heaven of the Angels at the converſion of a ſinner, by which it is clear, that they muſt know when every ſinner is converted; or how ſhould they know when to rejoyce: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the tran figuration of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him and talked with him; ſo that if they (being out of this world) had not known of his being on Mount <hi>Thabor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 9. ver. 4.</note> how ſhould they have waited upon him: And again, our Saviour ſaith. That his Apoſtles ſhall ſit with him in judgement,<note place="margin">Mat. 19. ver. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and judge the twelve Tribes of Iſrael:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Saints ſhall judge the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. ver. 1.2.</note> which could not be, if they did not know what paſſeth in the world; for in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, no Judge can or will paſs Sentence upon any man before he knows what he is guilty of: by all which it is as manifeſt and clear (as to ſee the Sun when it ſhines in the Firmament) that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152613:20"/>Angels and Saints know what paſſeth here on earth.</p>
               <p>Again, it is very much to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to conſider what paſſed at the Death of Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> where the Text ſaith, He looked into heaven,<note place="margin">Acts 7. ver. 54, 55, 56.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſaw the glory of God, and Jeſus ſtanding at the right hand of God, and ſaid, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I ſee the heavens opened, and the Son of Man ſtanding at the right hand of God;</hi> from whence it is evident and plain, that if Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> could upon earth ſee into heaven, where God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was, that he can now, being glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in heaven ſee and know what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon earth, in a far larger mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo may be prayed unto for his aſſiſtance;<note place="margin">Ver. 60.</note> for if he at his Death had ſo much charity to pray for the pardon of his enemies, that did not deſire it, we need not queſtion but his charity is much more now, and will be infinitely more ready to pray to God for thoſe that are his friends and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Church, which do heartily beg it of him; and as we ſee his prayer then took effect with God, for the converſion of his chiefeſt enemy,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152613:21"/>
                  <hi>Saul,</hi> which was preſently after; ſo we may juſtly hope, that God will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his graces upon us, by his holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion.</p>
               <p>But for your further inſtruction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what knowledge God gave to all the Prophets of old time, to foretell all thoſe great things that happened in the world in our Saviours time, and ſince, which we know were all true; and if God gave ſuch power to men when they were upon earth, do we think that God deprives Angels, or thoſe Prophets that are now in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory, of that power; or that Chriſts bleſſed Mother, which prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied that <hi>all generations ſhould call her bleſſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1. ver 48.</note> doth not know that ſhe is ſo called by all generations; it were a madneſs beyond compare to imagine ſuch a fooliſh thing, which is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expreſs word of God. I ſhall now conclude my diſcourſe of this ſubject with one example, which I think, had there been no Scripture to have proved what I have ſaid, would be of force enough, with any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſon to induce them to the belief of it.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152613:21"/>
               <p>We all know by our faith, that the Devil was once an Angel of heaven, and ſince his fall from that happy place, it is all his deſign to make us miſerable; and we all by ſad experience know, that he knows all our actions, as when we would do good he ſtrives to hinder us, and when we intend to do evil, he ſets us forward in the performance of it: Nay, when we do not intend evil, he puts it into our mindes to do it, and all the ſins we commit is from the Devil; and I pray, how came he by this power, but only as he was once an Angel of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? let us not think God gave him this power ſince he was a Devil of Hell; or that God which dearly loves our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as is plainly ſhown by him in the Death of his Son for us) would give more power to the Devil to work our deſtruction, then he doth to the good Angels which deſire and aſſiſt us in our ſalvation; we know too well, that he leads thouſands to ſin at one time, and do we not think the holy Angels endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ſame to lead us to vertue; we know, or may know to our coſts, that he is watchful and diligent to bring us to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152613:22"/>ruine, and do we not think the Angels are as careful to guard us from it; ſo that for any one to deny this truth, muſt certainly be poſſeſt with an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſpirit, which will ſhut its eyes againſt all Chriſtian verities. Now what hath been ſaid chiefly of the Angels is the ſame of the Saints in heaven, which are in the ſame place, and glory, and eſteem with God, according to that of our bleſſed Saviour, ſpeaking to the Sadduces about the Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Luke 20. ver. 36.</note> That they which ſhould be worthy to obtain heaven ſhould dye no more, but ſhould be equal to the Angels. Thus having as I think ſhown ſufficiently the truth of this point, I ſhall next proceed to ſhew you how we may lawfully (without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to Chriſts Interceſſion) deſire them to pray to God for us; and with this conclude, that certainly God will never permit thoſe the ſociety of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that live and dye in ſo poor and beggarly eſteem of thoſe glorious ſpirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152613:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Proving, that ſince it is evident that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints can hear our prayers, we may lawfully pray to them as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſours for us to God.</head>
               <p>IT is a thing not a little to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when we conſider that man which by nature loveth thoſe things which may make him happy, ſhould yet himſelf be the onely obſtacle of his not being truly ſo; we all naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire heaven, but through the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that nature in us, we take the wrong courſe to obtain it; for what wiſe man can think that they which hate ſociety with Angels and Saints whilſt they are on earth, can ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that happineſs in heaven, ſince thoſe that touch at the honour of them, touches the apple of Gods eye; as our Bleſſed Saviour ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples when they were upon earth, <hi>He that hateth you, hateth me; and he that loveth you, loveth me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10. v. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>And if any one give but a cup of cold water in the name
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152613:23"/>of a Diſciple, he ſhould not loſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> ſo dear are all his ſervants to him, and if ſo while they are on this dunghill earth, ſure they are much more dear to him in his Palace of Heaven; and we can no wayes bonour God more (next to the Worſhip of himſelf) then by reſpecting and having communion with his heavenly Citizens, whilſt we are on earth; and beſides it is an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Faith in the Creed, <hi>I believe the Communion of Saints,</hi> which we that are on earth can no wayes do, but by our praying to them, and their praying for us; and this is the true Communion of Saints.<note place="margin">Gen. 48. v. 16.</note> Agreeable to this ſhall you finde in Holy Scripture, how <hi>Jacob,</hi> after he bleſſed his Son <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> he invokes an Angel to bleſs <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> Sons, ſaying, <hi>The Angel which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me from all evil bleſs theſe lads;</hi> ſo here you ſee it was the practice of this holy man, by which we may have the leſs reaſon to ſcruple it: but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what he ſaith more, <hi>And let my name, and the names of my Fathers Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and Iſaac be named by them;</hi> which infers, that they ſhould invoke their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152613:23"/>names in the behalf of their obtaining any thing from God; and it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently mentioned in Scripture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring mercy from God for <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſake, and for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Davids</hi> ſake; all this we know to be true, and will it think you diſpleaſe God to deſire mercy from him, for the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> ſake, or St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſake,<note place="margin">Job 5. v. 1.</note> who were as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons as ever the other were: ſo we may ſee in holy <hi>Jobs</hi> time it was practiſed, for <hi>Eliphaz</hi> upbraiding of him, ſaith, <hi>Call now,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 1. ver. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>if there be any that will anſwer thee, and to which of the Saints wilt thou turn?</hi> ſo in the Prophet <hi>Zachariah,</hi> we finde an Angel praying for <hi>Jeruſalem, Then the Angel of the Lord anſwered and ſaid, O Lord of Hoſts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and on the Cities of Judah, againſt which thou haſt had indignation theſe threeſcore and ten years:</hi> now what can be deſired more plain then theſe places are, if we are not wilfully blinde. It will cauſe every one both to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and practice of this ſacred Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thoſe bleſſed ſpirits, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152613:24"/>is in ſome meaſure an anticipation of the fruition of heaven. But yet to make it more manifeſt (to the intent that either you muſt deny Scripture or confeſs this truth) ſee what Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith in his Goſpel, that the rich man being in hell, prayed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> which I hope you will ſay is a Saint, <hi>And he cryed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16. v. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſaid, Father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, have mercy on me, and ſend Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water to cool my tongue, for I am tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in this flame;</hi> from which we may gather, that if this damned man prayed and hoped for mercy, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for him by <hi>Abraham</hi> (to whom he chiefly applyed himſelf) is it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to think that Chriſtians which are in hopes of heaven, and in the ſtate of Grace may not do the ſame to <hi>Abraham,</hi> or any the other Saints,<note place="margin">Ver. 25.</note> with more hopes then he could have, and better ſucceſs; and you may read here that <hi>Abraham</hi> heard him (where ere he was) and told him it could not be done, becauſe he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed his pleaſures in this world, and the other pains: ſo by this we may ſee,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152613:24"/>that the practice of this Article of Faith is not grounded upon weak foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, but on the Infallible Word of God which cannot deceive us, unleſs we deceive our ſelves by the miſapply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
               <p>Beſides let every Chriſtian conſider what a great folly they are guilty of, when they ſay the Angels do not know this, nor the Saints do not know that, (and ſo muſt not be prayed to) when we do not know the nature of our own ſinful ſouls, that is within us, and yet will be ſo vain, as pretend to know the power and nature of thoſe glorious Spirits, who in knowing God do know all things; and by our having Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, we have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Bleſſed Trinity; by our praying to them God is ſo much the more honoured, as they are in Dignity and Deſert above us; and as we know by experience that a King granteth ſooner the deſires of a mean Subject by the Mediation of his grand Favourite; ſo in reaſon we may believe that the King of Heaven will do the ſame to us, by the Mediation of his Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152613:25"/>The common objection by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and others is, that our Saviour faith, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will refreſh you.</hi> This was Chriſts goodneſs to invite us to come to him; and how poor a ſhift this is for them to prove that we muſt not pray to Angels and Saints ſhall appear plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for if becauſe Chriſt invites us to come to him, we muſt not apply our ſelves to any others, then we muſt not pray one for another as Saint <hi>James</hi> commands us:<note place="margin">Jam. 5. v. 16.</note> then why do we deſire Prieſts, or Miniſters to pray for us when we are ſick, and upon many other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions wherein we have need enough? onely becauſe we think their prayers to God is more acceptable then our own: now, all this is done without derogation to Chriſt; nay, you know it is to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory to pray one for another, &amp; we all account it a great charity; and if it be ſo, then there is no doubt but that we may deſire the bleſſed Saints to pray for us to God, through the merits of Chriſt, and it will redound more to his glory then our praying one for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other can poſſibly do.<note place="margin">Rev. 5. v. 18.</note> One Text more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152613:25"/>I ſhall ſhew you, and not of ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern as to this point; in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Revelations, where he ſaith, the four and twenty Elders fell down before the Lamb (or Chriſt) having their harps and golden vials full of Odours, which are the Prayers of Saints: by which it is plain that they offered up their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Chriſt;<note place="margin">Ver. 3.4.</note> for ſo Saint <hi>John</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it himſelf, that theſe vials full of Odours were the prayers of Saints: and in the eighth Chapter he ſaith, <hi>And another Angel came and ſtood at the Altar, having a golden Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and there was given to him much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, that he ſhould offer it with the Prayers of all Saints, upon the golden Altar which was before the Throne; and the ſmoke of the Incenſe which came with the Prayers of the Saints aſcended up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God out of the Angels hand:</hi> ſo by this it is apparent, that we may pray to them, and that they do offer up our prayers to God, and pray for us. Now it will be neceſſary to clear that miſtake in Proteſtants, who think we make no difference between our praying to Chriſt, and our Interceſſion to Saints.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152613:26"/>
               <p>It would be a great Hereſie for any one to hold,<note place="margin">1 John 2. v. 1.</note> that the Power and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Chriſt ſhould not be far above all that of Angels or Arch-Angels and Saints in heaven;<note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. on this place.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to underſtand what kinde of Mediatour Chriſt is, and how he is our Advocate to the Father; <q rend="margQuotes">The Calling and Office of an Advocate is in many things proper to Chriſt, and to him onely it appertains to procure us Mercy from his heavenly Father, by the general ranſome, price, and payment of his Blood for our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as is in the Sentence following, He is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for our ſins onely, but for the ſins of the whole world; in which ſort he is our onely Advocate, becauſe he is our onely Redeemer; and hereupon he alone immediately by his own Merits, without the aid or aſſiſtance of any man or Angel in his own Name, and right, confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealeth in our Cauſes before God our Judge, and ſo procureth our pardon;</q> and this is the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Advocation that can be: by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152613:26"/>all which you may ſee that we Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks attribute to Chriſt in a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſort his power in his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, then Proteſtants do, or imagine, who make poor ignorants believe that none muſt mediate for us but Chriſt, thinking meerly by a bare ſhow of zeal to Chriſt, to null all other mediations, when by that means they diſhonour him, by comparing or valuing his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation at no higher a price, then we do Angels, Saints, and Mens. Now when we pray to an Angel or Saint, we deſire them to pray for us to God the Father, or the Bleſſed Trinity, that they would obtain for us of God, this, or that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that all is deſired through the Merits of our Saviour: And when we pray to Chriſt for any thing, we ought to pray to him as he is God, and not to ſay O Chriſt pray for me, (as we do to an Angel or Saint) for that were a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to him in making him of leſs pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the two other Divine perſons of the bleſſed Trinity, who is equal to both; and who in three perſons makes but one true and ever-living God, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152613:27"/>to all eternity. Should I produce the Authority and Practice of Gods Church, and the ancient Fathers, I might fill a large volume to confirm you; I will onely conclude with that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug Med. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> where invoking the Saints, he ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">O holy and Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> Mother of God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to intercede for me to him, whoſe Temple thou was deſerved to be made, holy <hi>Michael,</hi> holy <hi>Gabriel,</hi> holy <hi>Raphel,</hi> holy Quire of Angels, and Arch-Angels, Patriarchs, and Prophets, A poſtles, Evangeliſts, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Confeſſors, and all the Juſt; I humbly crave that you would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to intercede to God for me a poor Sinner, that I may be delivered from the Jaws of the Devil, and from Eternal Death.</q> 
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152613:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Shewing that in all Ages, Angels have been aſſiſtant to Man for his good, and that we ought to reverence the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory both of Angels and Saints, as they are the chief Attendants on the living God.</head>
               <p>IT is no wonder we are ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe glorious Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens Angels and Saints, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how the memory of them is ſlighted and contemned in this our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Age, and that men now adayes deſire no more ſociety with them, then they would do with thoſe that deſigns their ruine: ſo miſerably hath Satan depraved our natures, and ſuggeſted to us a ſlighting of thoſe. Bleſſed Spirits, to the intent he may draw us the more to his helliſh ſervice, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our utter deſtruction. But to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive a little thoſe that are thus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with this principle, I ſhall plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhow you many examples from holy Scripture, both of the great good they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152613:28"/>have done to many holy men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what Worſhip and Reverence they have done to the Angels.</p>
               <p>The firſt is from that of holy <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18. v. 2.</note> when the three Angels appeared to him, to let him know the good news of his having a Son; the Text ſaith, <hi>He ran to meet them from the Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, and bowed himſelf toward the ground.</hi> The ſecond place that of holy <hi>Lot;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19. v. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>And there came two Angels to Sodom at even, and Lot ſate in the gate of Sodom; and Lot ſeeing them, roſe up to meet them; and he bowed himſelf with his face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ground, and ſaid, My Lords turn in I pray you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> &amp;c. Now here I may demand, why the holy Scripture ſhould inſtance to us, their bowing with their faces to the ground, but onely to ſhow us, that as they are the heavenly Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours that kinde of reverence is due to them. Thirdly, when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel appeared to <hi>Joſhua</hi> by <hi>Jericho,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 5. v. 13.14.15.</note> he demanded who he was for; and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſaid, <hi>Nay, but as Captain of the hoſt of the Lord am I come;</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> fell on his face to the earth, and did worſhip; and the Angel bid him pull
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152613:28"/>off his ſhooes, for the place where he ſtood was holy ground. So here you ſee is, firſt the Angels aſſiſtance in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fight for them; and ſecondly, a high worſhip done to him, and the place where he ſtood, by pulling off his ſhooes: and yet ſo miſerably blinded are people now adayes, to think and ſay that theſe kinde of things are Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, not at all conſidering that it ever hath, that it is, and ever will be the practice of all holy men, to do this homage to them. Fourthly, an Angel appears to the Iſraelites at <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 2. v. 1.4.</note> and for their good, tells them of what things God had done for them; which when he had done, all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple lift up their voices and wept. Fifthly, an Angel appears to <hi>Gideon,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſtrengthen him againſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites;<note place="margin">Judg. 6. v. 12.22, 23.</note> and when he perceived it was an Angel of God, he was afraid he ſhould dye; till God told him he ſhould not: by which we may ſee what a reverend apprehenſion he had of the Angel Sixthly, an Angel appears to <hi>Sampſons</hi> Mother; and tells her (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing barren) the glad news of a Son: if
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152613:29"/>you read the whole Chapter,<note place="margin">Judg. 13. v. 3.</note> it is much to our purpoſe, both to ſee how the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angel converſed with his Father and Mother both; as alſo with what reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence they treated with him. Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we read that the holy Prophet <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> being a ſleep under a Juniper-tree,<note place="margin">1 Kings 19. v. 5.</note> an Angel awaked him, which brought him both to eat and drink in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs where he was, and where no bread was to be had; and the Angel appeared to him the ſecond time,<note place="margin">Ver. 6.</note> and he roſe and eat what the Angel brought him; and by vertue of that went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes and forty nights on his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. A ninth place is of an Angel aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the people of God, in the ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Aſſyrians,<note place="margin">Iſa. 37. v. 36.</note> 185000. men, which came againſt them, and <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> their King. Again, in the Book of <hi>Tobias</hi> we read of many good things done by the Angel <hi>Raphel,</hi> as to young <hi>Tobias</hi> in guiding of him in his journey from all dangers,<note place="margin">Tobit. 3. v. 17.</note> in chaſing away, and binding the Devil <hi>Aſmodius,</hi> in curing of old <hi>Tobias,</hi> and many others of that kinde;<note place="margin">Chap. 12. v. 15.</note> and at laſt he tells him who he was, and how he was one of the ſeven
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152613:29"/>Angels that preſents the Prayers of the Saints,<note place="margin">Ver. 16.</note> and goes in and out before the holy One; then they were both trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and fell upon their faces for they feared; which trouble we may conceive was, becauſe they had not done him before the worſhip due to an Angel. I could produce many other places out of the old Teſtament to prove this; but I will now proceed to the new: and firſt of that moſt happy and ever bleſſed news of our Redemption, where the holy Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> was imployed for our eternal good, to declare to the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> the Incarnation of the Son of God in her Virginal Womb;<note place="margin">Luke 1. v. 26.27, 28.</note> we may devoutly imagine there paſſed much reverence between two ſuch creatures as they, which were in ſo high eſteem with God, the one to be his Mother, and the other his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador. Secondly, the ſame Angel came to <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Prieſt, and told him the glad tydings of his Son <hi>John;</hi> yet when he ſaw him he trembled, and was afraid, for very reverence to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. So again thirdly, two Angels ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to St. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 20. v. 12.</note> and the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152613:30"/>Diſciples to tell them the good news of our Saviours Reſurrection, which was no ſmall comfort to them; and after that an Angel viſits St. <hi>Peter</hi> in priſon, and breaks his gives, and chains, and opens the doors,<note place="margin">Acts 12. v. 7.8, 9, 10.</note> and the City Gates, and lets him free. Again, an Angel appears to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and aſſiſts him, by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling him to ſend for <hi>Peter</hi> about his ſalvation;<note place="margin">Acts 11. v. 3.4.</note> and when he ſaw the Angel he was afraid: nay, when Saint <hi>Peter</hi> came he fell down before him, as being a holy man; but his humility would not ſuffer him to continue ſo. In like manner the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was comforted by an Angel, when he was in his Shipwrack, as he himſelf wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth,<note place="margin">Acts 27. v. 23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>And there ſtood by me this night the Angel of God, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve, ſaying, Fear not Paul,</hi> &amp;c. by all which ſo plain and innumerable places of Scripture, it is made ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that I think no perſon that reads this Book can for ſhame any longer reſiſt ſo infallible a truth; for if he do, he muſt lye under the heavy cenſure of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer; who, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>is judged already.</hi> I hope that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152613:30"/>of thoſe (which ſay they will believe nothing but the Bible) will now fly in their faces, and bluſh for ſhame and confuſion, when they conſider how little of it they practice, and pretend to the Bible, barely for a ſhow of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to deceive themſelves and others. But further to proſecute this point (to the intent none but Heathens may deny it) we will conſider how Chriſts beloved Diſciple Saint <hi>John</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himſelf to the Angel that came to him ſo often in his Revelations;<note place="margin">Rev. 19. v. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>And I fell at his feet to worſhip him, and he ſaid unto me, Do it not, I am thy fellow ſervant;</hi> which words of the Angel, <hi>Do it not,</hi> is the main Argument againſt this practice, which Proteſtants have: but how poor an one it is, ſhall be ſeen; for I hope no man will think that Saint <hi>John,</hi> which was ſo great a Divine, and ſo eminent with Chriſt, could be ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant as not to know what Worſhip was due to an Angel, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Angel ſaid, <hi>Do it not,</hi> becauſe he knew that St. <hi>John</hi> was in as high eſteem with God as himſelf was; and beſides, St. <hi>John</hi> did do it again to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152613:31"/>the Angel,<note place="margin">Rev. 22. v. 8.</note> that is, <hi>fell down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him;</hi> which we may be ſure he never would have done, being told of it before, if it had not been lawful; for then he would have been guilty of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, which I hope no good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an will tax him with: But this buſineſs between the Angel and Saint <hi>John,</hi> is juſt as when two ſpecial friends meet, for they ſtrive who ſhall give the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt reſpect to each other, yet will not ſeem to admit of any worſhip extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary from each other: ſo we ſee by the firſt Text, that the Angel would not admit of Saint <hi>John</hi> to worſhip him, becauſe his humility thought him his equal, and as he ſaith, his fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: and b the ſecond Text we ſee St. <hi>John</hi> would not forbear worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him, becauſe his humility thought him ſuperiour. So hoping that I have ſufficiently ſatisfied the Chriſtian Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in this point, I will now briefly ſhow thee how vaſt a difference there is in the Worſhip that is due to God, and in that which is due to Angels and Saints.</p>
               <p>And firſt we are to conſider that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152613:31"/>there is a Divine Adoration, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip due to God, which if it be given to either Angels, or any thing created, it is flat Idolatry; for ſince God is the Creator of us all, it is fit that he ſhould have a Worſhip given to him above all that he hath created; and therefore it is a moſt ſtrange abuſe that is put upon the holy Catholick Church, by thoſe that ſay (by our Worſhipping Saints and Angels) Chriſt is robbed of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, when indeed Chriſt is honoured by it (as is before plainly proved) ſince we acknowledge and give to him a far higher Worſhip then to all the Angels and Saints in Heaven; for what Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we give to them is as they are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpirits, and have ſo near relation to God, which would plainly appear to every ones experience, if once this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till juggle of Satan were laid open to our eyes, which is the bare pretence onely of giving all to God, which takes much with common underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, without conſidering that God is worſhipped by us, in a far higher man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and that Gods Worſhip is exalted in our reſpect, and reverence to them:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152613:32"/>as for example, this now is plain to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones experience, that we reverence the Kings Chaires of State, his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers where they are, and the like; now theſe do not receive this worſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Chairs, or becauſe they be Chambers, but onely as they have ſo near relation to the King; and what we do to them is done to the King, and he that doth not ſo is accounted a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, and turned out of Court as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of the King; and if this will happen for the contempt of inſenſible things, which have relation to the King, what may we think will happen to thoſe that live and dye in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thoſe glorious Creatures, which are ſo near God, praiſing of him to eternity.</p>
               <p>So not queſtioning but this that hath been ſaid, will ſufficiently ſatisfie every impartial Reader, and induce him both to the Faith and Practice of ſo holy and reaſonable a thing, that ſo at laſt he may enjoy the bleſſed Society of the Principalities, Powers, Vertues, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, Thrones, Angels, Arch-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Cherubins, and Seraphins, with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152613:32"/>the holy Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt and all the Saints in heaven, with whom we had ſociety here on earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap 8.</hi> Proving that the Images of Chriſt and his Saints may be lawfully made and reverenced, as they have relation to the firſt Figure, contrary to the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>AMongſt all the bundles of errours that tumbles up and down in the mindes of men, and ſtrives to ſtifle truth, there is none more maliciouſly and publickly publiſhed, then is this againſt holy Images, whoſe bad Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors make too many believe, that it is no leſs then Superſtition to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, much more to ſhow any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to them: but to the intent that their eyes may be illuminated that are blinde for want of ſeeing them, I ſhall prove the quite contrary, as that it is a holy and good cuſtom, and very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152613:33"/>to our ſouls: but firſt I will clear that main objection, by which they ſay we are breakers of the Law, and ſo Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters; which is indeed ſo buzzed in the ears of the common people, that they have nothing more to ſay, but (Doth not the Lord ſay; <hi>thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image;</hi>) I could tell them, and truly enough, that he never did ſay ſo; for though their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles do ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image,</hi> the Tranſlator did but cobble it; for the meaning is plain, Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Idol, or painted, or any way at all to adore it as God, for that were plain Idolatry and Heatheniſh; for do we think that in the twentieth Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> God would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Images, and in the five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Chapter command them again to be made, as is plain to be ſeen; where in the command that God gave to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ver. 18 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>And thou ſhalt make two Cherubims of Gold, of beaten work ſhalt thou make them in the two ends of the Mercy-ſeat.</hi> And again, God ſaith to him, That there he would meet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152613:33"/>with him: now theſe Cherubims were the Images of the higheſt Order of Angels, and ſure they think God knew not what he did, in commanding theſe Images, if he had forbid them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And further, to ſhew you that abſurdity, obſerve that God likewiſe commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make the Image of a Brazen Serpent, and ſet it up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a pole, that thoſe which were ſtung with Serpents (as many were) ſhould look up to that image and be cured; <hi>And Moſes made a Serpent of Braſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 21. v. 8 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſet it upon a pole, and if a Serpent had bitten any man, he looked upon the Serpent of Braſs and lived:</hi> now one would think that this ſhould be Idolatry, ſo to look up to this Image, and be preſently cured, or cauſe them another time to do ſo, that were ſo prone to it, as the Jews were; but that they are we know it was God and not the Image that cured them. But now I would fain know from our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who was the firſt commander of Images to be made and ſet up? I hope they will ſay now that God was; for if they do not, they muſt belye Gods
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152613:34"/>word which muſt be truth, and their own Conſciences which may be falſe. It is enough to amaze a ſerious man when he conſiders the grand cheat that is put upon thouſands of poor ſouls, and the continual thundring out of Pulpits againſt Images. Oh theſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Images! when God knows they adore an Idol, which is their giddy fancy, by offering up their will, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and underſtanding, on its prophane Altar: for obſerve that if God had forbid Images, why do they picture Deaths Image in their Churches, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> lying in her Tomb, and the Marble Statues and Tombs of Kings, and other perſons, with Flags, Streamers, and Images of ſome Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and the like; let every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an judge, were theſe better then Chriſt, or his bleſſed Mother, or the Apoſtles; or were they better Benefactors to the Church then Chriſt hath been and his Diſcriples? for if it be no ſin, nor Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to ſet up thoſe in Churches, ſure it is none to ſet up Chriſts and his Saints Images. But perhaps you will ſay, we do not adore them as Gods, nor
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152613:34"/>pray to them, nor truſt in them; and I do aſſure you, that I will ſay, nor Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks neither, but do denounce a curſe againſt them that do adore, or pray, or truſt in them as Gods; for can any but ſenſeleſs creatures think, that we which adore God in ſpirit and in truth, and confeſs him to be three diſtinct Perſons, and one God, can be ſo ſottiſh as to think, that an Image or Picture can either hear, ſpeak, or ſee, much leſs to be truſted in as a God. Again, If Images were forbid, why do Proteſtants, nay, the Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deſire to have their own Pictures, and Wives, and Childrens, which are onely for Vanity, and not for Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all, as Chriſts and his Saints Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are? as I ſhall ſhow hereafter:) and beſides, there is no Proteſtant of the Profeſſion of Carving and Painting, but will make an Image of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, or any elſe for money, and do daily ſell them, as we all know; which if it were Idolatry, then were you guilty for making, ſelling, and keeping them too, which is as fooliſh to think as the other. And now having
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152613:35"/>ſufficiently proved the lawfulneſs of them, I will now ſhow what good uſe we have, and may have by them: as for example, I would fain know why an ignorant perſon or any other, may not receive knowledge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by ſeeing our Saviours bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſion painted, and plainly ſet forth, as to read it Printed upon Paper; for in that way we receive our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by the eye, and ſo do we by the Pictures: and I am ſure it is more do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous and piercing to ſee the perfect manner of his ſufferings Painted, then to read them Printed; though both be very good: beſides many times when our mindes are wandering after world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs, yea, in our prayers too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; then if we reflect our eyes upon thoſe heavenly Figures, as our Saviour and his Saints, it reduces our ſtrayed thoughts to God, and heaven, and to what our Bleſſed Saviour hath ſuffered for us; and ſo they are books to thoſe that cannot read, and great helps to Devotion, to them that can; and I am very certain, that if the greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of them in the world did uſe and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152613:35"/>practice them the ſame manner as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks do, it would (as juſtly it might) convert their hatred to a perfect love of them, and be much aſhamed that they have ſo long ſlandered Gods Church, and deprived themſelves of ſo great a good, by believing ſuch abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable untruths, wherewith ſhe hath been falſly charged withal; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I may totally root out of mens mindes thoſe common aſperſions caſt upon her, I ſhall adde a little to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, how and in what manner they are to be uſed, according to that of the Councel,<note place="margin">Coun. Trent.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">We command all Biſhops and others who have the Office and care of Teaching, that they diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtruct faithful people, teaching them that the Images of Chriſt, of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> Mother of God, and of other Saints, are to be had, and retained, eſpecially in Churches, and that due reverence be given unto them; not that there is any Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be believed to be in them, or power, for which they are to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, or that any thing is to be asked of them, or that confidence is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152613:36"/>to be put in them, as anciently the Gentiles did in their Idols: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the honour which is done to them is referred to thoſe who they repreſent.</q> Now by this alone you may ſee what this ſuppoſed Mountain of Image Worſhip is come to, which is ſo untruly thundered out in Pulpits againſt us; ſo that when we pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Image, we do not pray to the Image, nor when we look with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon them, we do not adore them: but as I ſaid before in the other Chapter, what reſpect is done to the Kings Chair of State, or Chamber of Preſence, or Picture, is referred to him and his Honour; ſo is it the ſelf ſame to chriſts, and his Saints Images: and as no man would take him for the Kings friend (but his enemy) that ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, break, or burn his Picture, or his Mothers, or his Favourites; ſo juſtly may we think them to be Chriſts enemies that have done all that to his, and his holy Mothers, and Saints, with as great ſcorn and contempt as might be, and all under the pretended zeal for the word of God, by which they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152613:36"/>have deceived many thouſands of poor ſouls; but now having as I hope ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved the verity of our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice herein, and the impoſtures of thoſe that profeſs the contrary, I leave it to every reaſonable man to judge whether it be lawful or no, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Council,<note place="margin">Nice.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">We do not offer worſhip to the matter, as Wood, or Stone, or painting in colours, but through theſe, being brought to the perſon repreſented by them, we give due honour to him, knowing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly that the reſpect to the Image paſſes to him who is repreſented by it.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Proving that Man hath Free Will to do Good, or not to do it, contrary to the Opinion of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>DId thoſe men which deny this point of Faith, but admit (in the height of their paſſions) either of reaſon or conſideration, they would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152613:37"/>bluſh for ſhame, when they ſhewed them what Traytors they are to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in robbing their natures of one prime quality which God hath given them for an ornament to the ſame; for take from man his free-will, and you may turn him, like a <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> amongſt the beaſts; for God (by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle) can make him do good actions in that form and nature; but for the want of prudent conſidering the actions of their lives, they run into as many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, as their giddy fancies pleaſes to ſuggeſt to them: but this is the miſery of moſt men, that when the Devil tempts them to theſe evils they will not reſiſt, but entertain all; and amongſt al his helliſh deceits he hath none that takes more with weak underſtandings, then this ſly trick of his ſeeming to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all to God, as he tempts Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to believe, that Angels muſt not be reverenced, nor Saints reſpected, nor prayed too, but all to God, which is his devilliſh ſlight, to hinder that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God (as I proved before) and that all mens good works, done by Gods holy Grace, are ſinful and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152613:37"/>nothing, onely to hinder and make men carefuleſs to do ſuch good works; and that man hath no free-will, onely to make man idle, and not ſtrive to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy thoſe graces that God hath been pleaſed to beſtow upon us: ſo that did all men but once diſcover theſe tricks of Satan, we ſhould eaſily ſee, that God is honoured by theſe things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are his gifts and benefits which he hath been pleaſed to beſtow on us to enrich our ſouls, and make us more capable of ſerving him. The truth of this ſhall be as plainly proved by Scripture and Reaſon, as any thing before treated of; that ſo we may lay open the ſhameful hypocriſie of thoſe that work their ſelf-ends, from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people, meerly through the blinde pretence of Scripture; which being ſo done, you will finde hem rotten at the very heat. And firſt of all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Cain,</hi> where God tells him,<note place="margin">Gen. 4. v. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou do well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doſt not well, ſin lyeth at thy door:</hi> ſo here it is plain, that God left it to his choice to do well, or not to do it. Again, God ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152613:38"/>I will rain bread from Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 16. v. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and the people ſhall go out and gather it every day, that I may prove them whether they will walk in my way or no:</hi> now if they had not had a free-will, why ſhould God ſay he owuld try them; ſo that you ſee God left them to their free-will, to ſee whether they would ſerve him better or no. Again, God ſaith to them in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 11. v. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold I ſet before you a bleſſing, and a curſe: a bleſſing if you will obey the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your God, and a curſe if you will not obey.</hi> Now conſider, that as this is plainly and truly, Gods word, ſo plainly and truly doth it ſhow free-will to be in man. Again, God ſaith to them in the ſame Book,<note place="margin">Chap. 28. v. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If you will hearken diligently to the voice of the Lord, thy God, to keep all his Commandments, I will ſet thee on high above all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and ſo tells them how many ſorts of bleſſing he will beſtow upon them, if they will keep his Commandments; but if they would no,<note place="margin">Ver. 15.</note> he tells them how many curſes ſhould light upon them. And in the ſame Book again he ſaith to them in a very ſtrange manner, <hi>I call
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152613:38"/>heaven and earth to record this day againſt you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 30. v. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>that I have ſet before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing; therefore chooſe life that thou and thy ſeed may live:</hi> I might juſtly ſtand amazed here at theſe Texts of Gods word, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire with what face men can ſay they believe the Bible, and not tremble when they ſay ſo; conſidering how they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this free-will in man (which God hath given him) and other principles of Chriſtian Religion proved before; for here we ſee God himſelf layes it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and leaves it to us; and what would we have God do more, unleſs he ſhould work Miracles daily, and we lye like beaſts or ſtones and do nothing. The ſame did God offer to <hi>David</hi> by his Prophet <hi>Gad,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">2 ſam. 24. v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>God and ſay unto David, thus ſaith the Lord, I offer thee three things, chooſe the one of them that I might do it unto thee:</hi> Now here, God would not execute his Juſtice on <hi>David</hi> till he had choſen what puniſhment he would himſelf, that might be moſt for his good. And to his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> God ſaith likewiſe,<note place="margin">1 King. 6. v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou wilt walk in my Statutes, and execute my Judgements,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152613:39"/>and keep all my Commandments, then will I perform my word with thee:</hi> by all which is ſtill more plain, that <hi>Solomon</hi> had a free-will. Now though this that hath been ſaid might ſerve ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to convince thoſe that have held the contrary, and deſire to imbrace the truth of Gods word in reality; yet I will proceed for their further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and knowledg of the truth in this point; and firſt out of the Goſpel of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> where our Saviour cryes out,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. v. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, how often would I have gathered you to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as a hen doth her Chickens, but you would not;</hi> ſee here how Chriſt complains of them, becauſe they would not imploy their wills in his holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as he would have had them done; for ſaith he, <hi>I would, but you would not.</hi> and in another place he ſaith, <hi>I thou wilt enter into life keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> ſo that in every place it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to our free-will, to do and not to do any good action, as is plain by all theſe places of Scripture; by which you may ſee what folly they are guilty of, that ſay we have none, or that it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152613:39"/>takes away the honour from God, which can no wayes be; for ſince we ſay that free-will in us is a gift from God, and the good actions we do by that will, is inſpired into us by God, then is God the Original of all, and we onely the inſtruments of doing it, or not doing it; for we all know that God often inſpires us to good actions which we never do (to our ſhame we may ſay it) and that he would have us to do them is clear, or elſe he would not inſpire us. Now God having done his part in inſpiring of us, he leaves us then to our free-wills, to do it, or not to do it; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his chaſtity, <hi>I could wiſh that all men were as I am:</hi> but if men had not free-wills to be ſo, it were in vain for him to wiſh any ſuch thing. Of all the evil opinions that are held by men, there is none ſo ſenſleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as this; for I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them that deny it, wherefore they go to hear Sermons, if they have not a free-will to do what is there ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to them by the Preacher; and wherefore they read the Bible if they
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152613:40"/>have not a will to do what is there commanded (for it is not the bare reading of it will ſave their ſouls) why do they chide and beat their Children and Servants, for not going to Church, and ſerving God, if they have not a free-will to do it? why have they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Catholicks for not coming to their Churches, if they had not a free-will to do ſo; and to what purpoſe ſhould God give us his Laws to keep, and threaten us with damnation if we keep them not, if we had no free-will to keep them; and no man would think it otherwiſe then unreaſonable, if a King ſhould command him to do a thing, and threaten him with death if he did it not, and he had no will nor power to do it: But I would have thoſe men know, that God is too mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful in his nature, then everlaſtingly to puniſh us, for that which lyes not in our power to do, and that at this rate they would make God a Tyrant over us, that is ſo infinitely good to our ſouls and bodies. And laſtly, why are men puniſhed, and hanged, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the Law of Juſtice for their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152613:40"/>evil deeds, if they had not had a free-will to have done otherwiſe, all theſe puniſhments would be unreaſonably inflicted; and no man deſerves any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for the worſt of crimes, if he had no free-will to do that which is good: and the greateſt ſinner in the world, might at the Day of Judgement demand of God what reaſon he hath to damn him for doing ill, if he never had enjoyed a free will to have done good. And now having as I think ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved this verity, I ſhall proceed to another ſubject, as plainly declared in Scripture as this, and ſo conclude with this truth, that certainly God would never have commanded us to walk in conformity to his will, if we have not free-will to perform it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:152613:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Proving that good Works done in the ſtate of Grace are Meritorious, contrary to Proteſtants Opinion.</head>
               <p>WEre the mindes of men to be ſearched into, and known one by the other, it would plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the tongues of many ſpeak far contrary then what nature hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon their hearts, and that for ſome intereſt or other they give their conſciences the lye, rather then they will yield from their obſtinate opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for to contradict the merit or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of good works, plainly ſhowes they ſpeak againſt that which they would not be deprived of themſelves: ſo plainly is it agreeable to our natures to expect it, and in Scripture often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to us, as ſhall be made appear. And firſt from our Saviour himſelf in Saint <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, where ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us how we ſhould deal our almes in ſecret,<note place="margin">Matth 6. v. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>And thy Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which ſeeth thee in ſecret, himſelf ſhall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152613:41"/>reward thee openly:</hi> ſo here is a promiſe of our Saviour, that almes done in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſhall be rewarded, if we dare to take his word for it; by which it is plain that they merit that reward from God, yet not as they barely proceed from us neither, for it is Gods godneſs to inſpire the doing of them in us, and his gift too in making them meritorious; and in the want of this diſtinction lies the ſubtilty of Satan, and our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who make poor ſouls believe that Papiſts (as they call them) truſt to their merits ſo far, as not having any need of Chriſts Merits, think to be ſaved barely by their own: but when ſuch untruths as theſe are be-preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the people from pulpits (as my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge can verifie, and many thouſands more) it is no wonder the common people have prejudicate Opinions againſt Catholicks: But to undeceive them again, I will ſet down the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Decree of Gods Church concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point;<note place="margin">Coun. Trent.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">God forbid that any Chriſtian ſhould hope in truſt in his own Merits, but in the Merits of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whoſe goodneſs is ſo great
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152613:42"/>to mankinde, that thoſe things that are his Benefits he will have to be our Merits: by which it is apparent, that we do not, nor ought not to attribute any merit as they proceed from us barely, but as being the gifts of God, which is pleaſed to accept of good works from us, and out of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reward them, as he hath promiſed he will.</q> But now to Scripture, and ſee what we can gather more from thence; where in Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> our Saviour ſhowing how hard it was for a rich man to enter into heaven, becauſe he could not leave the things of this world,<note place="margin">Matth. 19. v. 27.28.</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> cryes out, <hi>Behold, we have forſaken all, and when ſhall we have;</hi> ſo that it is evident, he expected a reward from our Saviour: and in the next verſe he tells them what their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhould be, <hi>That when the Son of man comes to ſit in his glory, they ſhould ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Iſrael:</hi> and as this ſhows the bounty of Chriſt in reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſo highly, ſo it ſhows like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that their good works in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, and ſuffering for him, had
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152613:42"/>ſerved it, ſo far as was poſſible in men to do. Again, we read of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> pouring a box of Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on our Bleſſed Saviours head; which being murmured at by his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, he ſaid unto them,<note place="margin">Matth. 26, v. 7, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Why trouble ye the woman, ſhe hath wrought a good work upon me;</hi> and then he declares her reward, which was, that ſo far as the Goſpel was to be preached,<note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> ſhould her fame be ſpread: conformable to this our Saviour in Saint <hi>Marks</hi> Goſpel ſaith to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Mark 9. v. 41.</note> that <hi>whoſoever ſhall give you a cup of water to drink in my name, becauſe ye belong to Chriſt, Verily I ſay unto you, he ſhall not loſe his reward.</hi> Now what can be more true then this, when our Saviour himſelf ſo often doth promiſe rewards for good works done in his name, and for his ſake; and let every Chriſtian conſider, whether they are not bound to believe him, before thoſe that tell them the contrary, who plainly contradict Chriſt and his holy Goſpel; and yet forſooth theſe men make you believe their zeal is ſo hot to Chriſt, that they will give all to him, to make you believe they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152613:43"/>deny themſelves: but theſe are ſuch, who as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>are ravening Wolves.</hi> But again, our Saviour ſaith in Saint <hi>Marks</hi> Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mark 10. v. 29, 30.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no man that hath left houſe, or lands, or Wife and Children for my ſake and the Goſpels, but he ſhall receive an hundred fold here, and in the world to come eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life.</hi> Thus in many places is this truth made ſo clear to us by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that I hope none will be ſo much an Infidel as to practice the contrary. But further to ſhow you this truth, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this notable place concerning this point, where our Saviour ſpeaking concerning the general day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, declares for what cauſes ſome are ſaved and ſome damned; for to the juſt he ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 25. v. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you;</hi> and then in the next verſe he tells them for what cauſes they are made eternally happy;<note place="margin">Ver. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>For I was a hungry and you gave me meat, I was thirſty and you gave me drink, naked and you clothed me,</hi> &amp;c. And the reaſons why them on his left hand received the ſentence of hell fire, was becauſe they did not do
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152613:43"/>theſe good works which the other had done;<note place="margin">Ver. 41, 42.</note> and ſo as the juſt by good deeds had obtained heaven, ſo the wicked by their evil ones had obtained hell. Now I verily think that if a Heathen, or Jew ſhould read this Book, they would ſay it was rather made for inſtructing them in the Faith of Chriſt, then for thoſe that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and to believe the Bible, and yet to deny all this thus proved by the Bible. Now having proved this by the words of Chriſt, we will ſee what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his Apoſtle ſaith, who I will warrant you is of the ſame minde, as you ſhall ſee by his words to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Now he that planteth and he that water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth are one, and every man ſhall receive his own reward, according to his own la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:</hi> by which words it is plain, that every man ſhall receive his reward, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he hath himſelf deſerved. And in the ſecond to <hi>Timothy</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I have fought the good fight, I have kept the faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 4. v. 7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>henceforth is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſs, which God the righteous judge will give me at that day, and to all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152613:44"/>that love his appearing.</hi> Now here we ſee that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> knew his reward for thoſe good works, and declares that all that loves Gods appearing ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded at the laſt day. And more in his Epiſtle to the Hebrews,<note place="margin">Heb. 6. v. 10.</note> he ſpeaks to the purpoſe in this point, <hi>That God is not unrighteous to forget you work, and labour of love which ye have ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his name, in that ye have miniſtred to the Saints.</hi> Now you may perceive St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Opinion, which was, that it would ſeem unjuſt in God if he ſhould not reward our good works: but as certain it is that God cannot be unjuſt, ſo is it as certain that he will reward our good deeds done in communion with his Church; which if our works did not deſerve or merit, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no reward at all; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary receive an eternal puniſhment. Again, Saint <hi>John</hi> Evangeliſt ſaith in the Revelation.<note place="margin">Rev. 3. v. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ſhall overcome ſhall thus be inveſted in white Garments, and I will not put his name out of the Book of Life, and I will confeſs his name before my Father, and before his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> And again,<note place="margin">Ver. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſhall overcome
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152613:44"/>I will make him a pillar in the Temple of my God, and he ſhall go out no more.</hi> And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ver. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ſhall overcome will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne.</hi> I might and could produce many more places out of holy Scripture to this purpoſe; but they that will not believe theſe, will not care for ten thouſand proofs made againſt their perverſe principles: but I will onely adviſe thoſe that have any care of their ſalvation, to conſider, firſt what Gods word (which is truth it ſelf) declares to them. And ſecondly, what the practiſe of our Church is in this and other points of Religion, and how agreeable to the ſame word, as is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhown: for in reaſon onely, is this apparent to all Chriſtians, that if God (as he doth) inſpire us to do all our good works, then muſt needs thoſe works be meritorious, becauſe God inſpired them to be done, and hath promiſed to reward the doing of them, according to that of Saint <hi>John, Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 22. v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>And behold I come quickly, and my reward is with me,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152613:45"/>to give every man according to his work.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Proving that Gods Church cannot Erre in her Doctrine of Religion, and ſo may be truſted in by every Chriſtian, contrary to Proteſtants opinion.</head>
               <p>DID the Adverſaries of Gods Church but conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, what authority, and courage, and order it hath exerciſed for this ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years, they would ſurely conclude that no government but that of Gods holy Spirit could ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the like; for by its authority it hath alwayes ſuppreſt, and beaten down Hereſies, and by her courage overcome all the torments and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, her enemies could invent to lay upon her; and by her Order, hath ever retained in her Members one uniform Faith and Obedience, in all places where her Doctrine hath been ſpread: which if it be granted, or can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that Gods Holy Spirit is at all times with his Church, to direct her in her Doctrine, I hope none will deny
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152613:45"/>but that then ſhe is infallible, and ſo cannot poſſibly be capable of Errour; and that it is ſo ſhall be made manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to appear, if you will believe Chriſt himſelf, who cannot deceive us; where in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel telling his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that he muſt go to his heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to prepare them places, at length he gives them and his whole Church this Conſolation, <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter, that he may abide with you for ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14. v. 16.</note> Now we all know that the Apoſtles were not to remain for ever upon earth, for they are dead and gone; ſo that this promiſe of Chriſt was to them, and his Church after them, which is to remain to the end of the world: and in the next verſe he tells them who this comforter ſhall be, <hi>Even the Spirit of truth, whom the world cannot receive.</hi> Now I would fain know how Gods Church can Erre in what ſhe declares to us of Faith,<note place="margin">Ver. 17.</note> when Gods Holy Spirit is with it. And again, <hi>But the Comforter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my Name, he ſhall teach you all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152613:46"/>things.</hi> Now we may be ſure, that ſince the Holy Ghoſt is to teach the Church all things, there can be nothing but Truth taught in the ſame Church; and I pray then where will your Errours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, but in your own boſoms. But ſee further the truth of this, our Saviour parting out of this world, tells his Apoſtles, <hi>That he would be with them, even to the end of the world;</hi> ſo that we have two Perſons of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity promiſed to aſſiſt the Church of God for ever,<note place="margin">Matth. 28. v. 20.</note> beſides God the Fathers Divine aid; and if this Church Erre with their guiding, then there can be no truth at all for us to be guided by; for this is as clear as the Sun, that if the Church of God be guided by an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Spirit it cannot Erre: And the Church of God is guided by an Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit; therefore the Church of God cannot Erre. And though I have made this good already, yet I will make it more plainly appear from Chriſts own words, where he exhorting Brethren to be reconciled one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; which if they will not do by reaſonable perſwaſions, they ſhould
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152613:46"/>tell the Church,<note place="margin">Matth. 18. v. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>and if they will not hear the Church, let them be as Heathens and Publicans:</hi> by which it is plain, that if the Church were not Infallible, Juſt, and free from Errour, our Saviour would never have tyed us to her Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our Faith and Manners, under ſo ſad a penalty as being a Heathen, if we do not hear and ſubmit to her; and therefore it is very neceſſary for every one to ſubmit to Gods Church, which is infallibly true, leſt they be Heathens in the eſteem of God, and Man; and conſequently out-lawes to the Kingdom of Heaven. Again, ſee what our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaith to this purpoſe, in the ſame Goſpel, <hi>And I ſay unto thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 16. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>that thou art Peter, and upon this rock will I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it:</hi> now if the Church could be erroneous, then you muſt deny this Goſpel to be true; for no Errours can be in the Church but by the prevailing power of the Devil, which is meant by Hell-Gates, and which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>ſhall never prevail againſt it:</hi> ſo by this we are certain the Church cannot Erre; and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152613:47"/>we may confidently confide in her in all matters of our Salvation. But for your further aſſurance, if our Saviour be not enough, I will ſhow you what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith concerning this truth, where he confirms all that hath been ſaid of it, ſpeaking to holy <hi>Timothy;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. v. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>But if I tarry long, that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave they ſelf in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and ground of the truth.</hi> Now here I might ſtop and ſay no more, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid enough; for if it be the piller, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of truth, and the ground from whence truth is derived, is it not mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous to think of Errour; and I would fain know in what place Chriſtians ſhould ever be free from errour in their Faith, if not in the Church of God; and for to ſay that there is no way to be free from it would be very ſtrange, for then all men would grope in dark uncertainties, which is quite contrary to the Qualities and Excellencies of Gods Church, as was foretold by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſpeaking of the Church of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Chap. 35. v. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>And an high way ſhall be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152613:47"/>there, and it ſhall be called the way of holineſs, and fools ſhall not erre therein;</hi> now if there be no poſſibility for fools to erre in it, certainly wiſe men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. But this is no ſmall ſubtilty of our Adverſaries to hold this opinion, well knowing that their Church hath been, and is full of errours; and that the gates of Hell hath prevailed againſt it, hath manifeſtly appeared, and doth now appear, when all that they can do cannot allay the furious ſpirits of one Kingdom, nor reduce them to any Obedience to their Church; ſo that if they did not hold this Opinion as an Article of their Church, all the world would ſee theirs was not the Church of God, becauſe it hath errours, by which they are forced to maintain it as well as they can, though it be againſt both Scripture and Reaſon too. Now that this Church of God is onely the Roman Catholick, is plainly ſhown al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, by her conformity to, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Gods holy word, in all her points of Faith, which ſhe teacheth Chriſtians to believe; and therefore all her enemies wrong her and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152613:48"/>too, in ſaying the contrary; for wheres they cry out the Roman Church was once the true Church of God, but ſhe is fallen from it: now as they never could prove the time when, nor the occaſion how, ſo is it impoſſible it ever ſhould, becauſe (as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhown) Gods Holy Spirit guides and directs it, that the Gates of Hell can never prevail to overthrow it, nor bring it to errour. And now having ſufficiently proved the Infallibility of Gods Church, I cannot but adviſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that hath any care of their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal welfare, to imbrace and believe what ſhe preacheth concerning the ſame, and ſo conclude with that of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Many things (ſaith he) with much reaſon, kept me in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Catholick Church; the conſent of people and Nations holds me, the Authority of the ſame Church which is riſen up by Miracle, nouriſhed with Hope, augmented by Charity, eſtabliſhed by its Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the ſucceſſion of Biſhops holds me therein; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch beginning in the See and Authority of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152613:48"/>whom God recommended the care of his Flock, is maintained to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time: laſtly, the name of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick holds me in it; and addeth, he would not believe the Goſpel it ſelf, if he were not aſſured of it by the Catholick Church.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Proving the Doctrine of Remiſſion of Sins, as commanded by Chriſt, and practiſed by his Apoſtles, contrary to the Opinion of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>WEre not the mindes of many men corrupted with imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principles, they could not be ſo evil as to queſtion, yea deny the gifts both of Grace and Nature, that God hath given both to Angels and Men, when we have much reaſon to adore and praiſe him, that he hath ſo much eſteem of any of our Nature, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſuch prerogatives upon them: amongſt which, this is not the leaſt that I am to treat of, concerning remiſſion
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152613:49"/>of Sins by a Prieſt: which though there be a grand miſtake in this Point amongſt Proteſtants, and we are abuſed in it; yet I ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance, and by his holy word, clear the miſtake, which may eaſily remedy the abuſe: for in all Myſteries of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, we are to conſult with Gods word, which (if rightly underſtood) cannot deceive us, and not with our own ſhallow underſtandings which ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may: neither are we to be led away with aiery fancies of our own, nor with a giddy multitude, nor ought the ſlanderous tongues of men to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in; but if you finde it plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Scripture, then are we bound to believe it: for this is a general crime in this Age, that men think nothing can be true if their narrow capacities cannot comprehend it; as if all the myſteries of our Faith were ſo open, for every ones underſtanding to enter the knowledge of them; which if they were ſo, then there were no need of Faith, becauſe Faith is onely required in thoſe things our natures cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and ſo might every Turk and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152613:49"/>Pagan be as good a Believer as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: therefore for the redreſs of this evil we are to underſtand whether Chriſt gave this power to his Apoſtles or no; for if they had the power to pardon ſins, as being the Heads of his Church, the ſame power muſt remain to their Succeſſours in that Church; becauſe otherwiſe all ſucceeding Ages would receive no benefit by that gift, which our Saviour gave for the good of us all that lay hold of it. And to prove that they had this power is plain and eaſie enough; firſt, from Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Goſpel, where our Saviour tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Saint <hi>Peter</hi> he would build his Church on him, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. v. 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>And I will give thee the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt binde on earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven:</hi> by which it is clear, that he had a great power given him to pardon or not to pardon, and that thoſe which he did not pardon on earth, ſhould not be pardoned in heaven, which is the ſame in Gods Church to this day; and therefore let every one
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152613:50"/>conſider what reaſon they have to be members of it, by which conſiſts our eternal ſalvation. Again, our Saviour tells his Diſciples in general, ſaying, <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall binde on earth ſhall be bound in heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and whatſoever ye ſhall looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> by which it is plain, that they had this power of remiſſion of ſins, and to deny the ſame power to their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in Gods Church would in my eſteem be very unreaſonable: And as in all other points of Faith, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of them proceeds from a want of a right underſtanding of them, as I have ſhown elſewhere, ſo is it the ſame in this; for it is buzzed in poor peoples ears, Can man pardon ſins, or can Prieſts forgive us, or the Pope abſolve us, without any conſideration of the nature of it at all; for if we rightly underſtood our ſelves, or did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with reaſon, we ſhould ſoon be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived in this myſtery: For in the firſt place know, that it is the gift of Chriſt himſelf, and therefore not to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by any man. Secondly, Prieſts cannot pardon ſins by any natural
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152613:50"/>power they have more then other men, but by a ſupernatural grace from God; we know and confeſs, that it appertains to God onely by nature to pardon ſins; and ſo doth many other things, as working of Miracles, and caſting out of Devils, and healing the ſick, and the like, which power we know God hath given unto men, as well as the other, proved by Chriſt himſelf, where he ſpeaking of all that truly believed in him, ſaith he, <hi>Theſe ſignes ſhall follow</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 16. v. 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>in my name ſhall they caſt out Devils, they ſhall ſpeak with new tongues, they ſhall take up Serpents, and if they drink any deadly thing it ſhall not hurt them; they ſhall lay hands on the ſick, and they ſhall recover:</hi> now it is certain, all theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies appertains to God by nature; but if he is pleaſed to give this power to men, what reaſon have we to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, or be offended with it; which power is equal to that of remiſſion of ſins, and we ſee are both given to men by God. Thirdly, we are to conſider, that Prieſts do not pardon our ſinnes immediately from themſelves, but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterially, as when they apply the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152613:51"/>words of Abſolution on us; God hath promiſed to pardon us, otherwayes he will not,<note place="margin">John 20. v. 23.</note> as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted; and whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained:</hi> ſo that you ſee this is plainly true, if you dare believe Chriſt himſelf. Now that this may not ſeem ſtrange to you, do but conſider that great vertue that is in Baptiſme; where by the application of water, and a few words by the Prieſt, or Miniſter, the childe is pardoned of all its original ſin: now it is not the Miniſter, nor Water, nor words, that pardons the Childe, but God himſelf, who is pleaſed by them, and that means, to do it; and yet it is ſo far from diſhonouring God, that he is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, becauſe it is his holy will it ſhould be ſo; and this all Proteſtants believe, which is as great a gift of God to mankinde, as is the other; and by all people thus plainly underſtood, will not appear ſo ſtrange and monſtrous, as they are made believe it is: now we may plainly ſee how far thoſe kinde of men are from being in Gods Church, that do not onely not practiſe this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152613:51"/>truth, but rail againſt and contemn it, though it be publiſhed by our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, for the good of the whole world Again, conſider, if God had not ordained this in his Church, how ſhould we know that our ſins are pardoned by God at all, or when they are ſo pardoned, but that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed when they do it on earth, he will do it in heaven; and this is our onely aſſurance, and as it were, a mark, by which we know our ſins are pardoned, that we may thank his Divine Name for it, which otherwiſe we ſhould be very uncertain when to do. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Chapter with that whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Counſel of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who deſireth, <q rend="margQuotes">That none make doubt of the Prieſts right in Remiſſion of Sins,<note place="margin">Aug. No. Teſt. q. <hi>53</hi>
                     </note> ſeeing the Holy Ghoſt is purpoſely given them to do the ſame; in which caſe if any be yet contentious, he muſt deny the Holy Ghoſt to be God, and not to have power to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſins:</q> And onely adde that of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">St. Amb. (lib. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>7.</hi> de peui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.)</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Why ſhould it be more diſhonour to God, or more impoſſible, or inconvenient for
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152613:52"/>men to forgive ſins by Pennance, then by Baptiſme, ſeeing that it is the Holy Ghoſt that doth it by the Prieſts Office and Miniſtery in both.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Proving the Churches <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality, and that no Church is, or can be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick but the Roman, againſt the Opinion of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>OF all the great actions that God hath openly done for mankinde, there is none that he hath declared more apparently, then that his Church ſhould be ſpread in all parts and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the whole world: to the intent that all Nations hearing the ſound of the Goſpel, there could be none that might plead any ignorance in the not hearing of it. Now as this ſhall be proved by the words of Chriſt himſelf, ſo I will firſt ſhow it you by the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Propheſies of the Prophets of God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 2. v. 2.</note> and firſt of <hi>Iſaiah, And it ſhall come to paſs, in the laſt dayes, that the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152613:52"/>Mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſts Church.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall be exalted above the hills, and all Nations ſhall flow unto it;</hi> ſo here is one true teſtimony, that the Catholick Church ſhall be ſpread in all parts, and all Nations ſhall partake of her holy Doctrine, and not to lye hid in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as in one Kingdome, or City, or Congregation, or this mans Church, or that mans Church, as all Sectaries do: by which I ſhall plainly prove they cannot be any thing like Gods Church. And again, the ſame Prophet ſaith, (ſpeaking of the many benefits that we ſhall enjoy under Chriſts Church) <hi>That the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 11 v. 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>as the waters cover the Sea;</hi> Now as we know they are ſpread in all parts of the world, ſo is the knowledge of Gods truth ſpread by his Church in the ſame manner; which quality agreeth to no other Church but the Roman Catholick. The ſame Prophet declares further,<note place="margin">Chap. 49. v. 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>That Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens thy nurſing Mothers;</hi> (and to ſhow the great reverence they ſhould
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152613:53"/>bear to this Church of God, (ſaith he) <hi>They ſhall bow down to thee, with their faces toward the earth, and lick up the duſt of thy feet.</hi> Now I would demand, what Church or Sect in the Chriſtian world, that hath Kings and Queens for their nurſing Fathers and Mothers, but the Roman Catholick; and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence cannot be the Church of God, but are as wandering ſheep having no true ſhepherd, and ſo are daily expoſed to the rage and fury of that ravening wolf,<note place="margin">John 10. v. 12.</note> the Devil. Again, the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaking how largely Gods Church ſhould be ſtretched forth under the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54. v. 2, 3.</note> ſaith, <hi>Enlarge the place of thy Tent, let them ſtretch forth the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of thine habitation, ſpare not, lengthen thy Cords, and ſtrengthen thy ſtakes; for thou ſhalt break forth on the right hand, and on the left, and thy ſeed ſhall inherit the Gentiles, and make the deſolate Cities to be inhabited.</hi> Now let the underſtanding Reader judge, where this Propheſie is fulfilled, in Proteſtants, and Sectaties, or in the Roman Church, which is thus ſtretched out, and hath her Members in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152613:53"/>
                  <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> in <hi>China,</hi> in <hi>Tartary,</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> in <hi>Turky,</hi> and all parts of Europe, as the Empire of <hi>Germany,</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Spain, France, Poland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Dominions of <hi>Italy:</hi> and every Land in Chriſtendom, is either all, or a conſiderable part of this Church, which none in the world can ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and ſo are very far off from ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling this Propheſie. And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Chap. 66. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs that I will gather all Nations and Tongues, and they ſhall come and ſee my glory.</hi> Thus hath this holy Prophet by Gods inſpiration foretold clearly the Univerſal or Catholick State of the Church of God in the time of the Goſpel; and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet hath not been ſilent in Propheſying the fame, for ſaith he,<note place="margin">Jer. 31. v 37.</note> 
                  <hi>If heaven above can be meaſured, and the foundation of the earth ſearched out beneath, then will I caſt off the ſeed of Iſrael, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring line ſhall go forth from Gareb to compaſs about Goath;</hi> all which do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the large extent of Chriſts Church. And for confirmation of theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152613:54"/>and what elſe hath been ſaid, I ſhall produce now the words of our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, who telling his Diſciples of all the troubles they were to ſuffer for his name before Kings and Judges;<note place="margin">Ma k 13. v. 10.</note> but ſaith he, <hi>The Goſpel muſt firſt be publiſhed among all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> which plainly ſhows that Gods Church muſt be Catholick or Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal: and I would fain learn from our Adverſaries, what Church hath taken the pains to publiſh the Goſpel to all Nations (and ſo fulfil theſe Propheſies) but the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> for this may be urged to the ſhame of all Sects, that if none took more pains in converting of Heathens, Jews, and Infidels then they do, many millions of ſouls might periſh for want of the knowledge of the living God: but they inſtead of labouring to convert forreign Nations, and ſo make the Church Univerſal lie at home in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the world, jangling one with another, and ſleeping on beds of Doun in Ladies boſoms; and yet by all means theirs is the true Church, and they the onely Paſtors ſent to convert the world,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152613:54"/>and yet never intend to go about any ſuch matter. It is a wonderful thing to conſider, that men that read the Bible, and all theſe Propheſies, can be ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant to think that Gods Church ſhould be pinn'd up in ſo narrow limits as any one Sect, or Congregation: did Chriſt himſelf preach for that, and command his Apoſtles to publiſh the Goſpel to all Nations? who did ſo, and loſt their lives in that work? was all this done, I ſay, to have his Church thruſt up in a corner, and to be no where elſe? how then ſhall all Nations come to know God, how ſhall they be Baptized, <hi>in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt?</hi> how ſhall they partake of any Sacraments? how ſhall the Church hear their differences,<note place="margin">Mat. 18. v. 17.</note> and decide them, as our Saviour ſaith it ſhall? how I ſay ſhall all this be done, if it were ſo ſtraitned? but ſince ſhe is a Catholick Church, ſhe is every where: and ſo all perſons (inſpired by God) in all places may receive, if they will, the foreſaid benefits, which otherwiſe can never be done. And thus is plainly ſhown you that there is an Univerſal
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152613:55"/>Church; and that it is the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, is as plain in its agreement with Gods Word, according to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who highly commends the ſame Faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 1. v. 7, 8.</note> in theſe words, <hi>To all that be in Rome, beloved of God, called to be Saints, grace to you, and peace from God our Father, and from our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: Firſt I thank my God for you all, that your Faith is ſpoken of through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world:</hi> from which words we may gather, that if the Faith of the Romans was ſo inlarged in the world ſixteen hundred years ago, that now it is much more; for then Gods Church was but in her Infancy, and now ſhe is in her flouriſhing State; ſhe was then under moſt cruel perſecutions by Tyrants, and now (praiſed be God) ſhe is at reſt with her friends: ſo that now we may clearly ſee, that all thoſe that are ſhut up in ſuch narrow Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, are meerly Sects and Hereſies, and are clean ſhut out from the boſom of the Spouſe of Chriſt, which is his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church; and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are in a very dangerous ſtate, as to the ſalvation of their ſouls. Our
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152613:55"/>Saviour doth further demonſtrate this extent of his Church by the ſimilitude of a grain of Muſtard-ſeed,<note place="margin">Mark 4. v. 31, 32.</note> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at firſt very ſmall, it groweth to a great tree; ſo that the fowls of the aire makes their neſts therein: even ſo the Church was at firſt very ſmall, but now it is ſo ſpread over the face of the earth, that all men may make their neſts, that is, come into her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and be ſecure of their ſalvation, living according to her holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which you ſee are agreeable to the Divine Word of God. Again, Chriſt ſaith (ſpeaking of the viſibility of his Church in the world) A City ſet upon a hill cannot be hid;<note place="margin">Mat. 5. v. 14, 15.</note> neither do men light a Candle, and put it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Buſhel, but on a Candleſtick, and it giveth light to all in the houſe: Now this light that Gods Church was to give by this here ſpoken by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, is not at all ſeen to forreign parts, by any Church, but the Roman Catholick, who hath the light of her Doctrine as far extended, as the Sun hath his beams; when all others being but in Corners at home, can give no
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152613:56"/>light at all to any; which clearly ſhows none of them can be Gods Church, but of the Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; for they have none of the marks of the true Church, ſo plainly ſet down in Scripture as to be Catholick or Univerſal, and to be viſible in all Ages, to be at union and peace one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to convert Nations, and ſeveral others, which they have none; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of univerſality, and being ſpread all over the world, many of them will not make ten Pariſhes in ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and the beſt of them ſcarce a whole Kingdom in the whole world: and inſtead of being viſible to all ages, the names of Proteſtants, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, and the reſt, were never heard of a hundred and ſixty years paſt: and as for their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Faith, which Chriſt left his Church as a mark, I leave to all people to judge, how much that belongs to any of them, that have ſeen and known theſe twenty years confuſion about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Church of God, <hi>If any man be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious we have no ſuch cuſtome.</hi> And for
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152613:56"/>their converting of Nations, I am ſure they will not boaſt of that themſelves, ſince they never did any. By all this it is plain, that as the Roman Church hath all theſe properties, ſo ſhe muſt be, and is this onely true Catholick and Apoſtolick, (or none at all) and from her muſt we receive our Faith, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of our Creed; <hi>I believe in the Holy Ghoſt, the Holy Catholick Church;</hi> ſo that they that deny the Church to be Catholick, or the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, do plainly deny their own Bibles, and the Apoſtles Creed; which are the Articles of our Faith. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid enough on this ſubject for all reaſonable people, I will conclude with that ſaying of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtin. tract. <hi>1.</hi> in Ep. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">For albeit particular hills in one Countrey may be unknown in another, (yet ſaith he) a Mountain that paſſeth through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Countreyes, and filleth up the whole world, (as <hi>Daniel</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Church of Chriſt ſhould do) cannot but be apparent to the ſight of all men,<note place="margin">Dan. 2. v. 44, 45.</note> but onely of ſuch as illingly ſhut their eyes from the ſight thereof.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:152613:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Proving that Faſting on certain Dayes commanded by Gods Church to be lawful and good, contrary to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>HAd Almighty God when he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated man a reaſonable creature, to do his will, and to live in ſobriety and temperance, made him an Epicure, and deſigned him for no other purpoſe, he could not have lived either in more contempt or leſs practice of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vertue, then the people of our Age do; who indeed look upon all the rare Examples and holy Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Bleſſed Saviour, as things indifferent, and of no concern at all to them; nay, are ſo far from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of them themſelves, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride and ſcorn thoſe that do; as if it were a crime to be vertuous, or to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the examples and, commands of our Saviour, who in many places of his holy word hath exhorted us to the good work of Faſting, as very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152613:57"/>to ſubdue our ſenſual appetites, and to obtain heaven. This will evidently appear, if you confult with Holy Writ, where we ſhall firſt ſee our Saviours great example in faſting forty dayes and forty nights;<note place="margin">Mat. 4. v. 2</note> and I would gladly know wherefore he did ſo, if not for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a good life; for he never committed ſin, and therefore did not require to do any ſuch thing for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and I think no man will ſay he did it for pleaſure, by which it is plain that he faſted for our example: but the common objection is, can you faſt as Chriſt did, if not, to what purpoſe is yours done? he faſted forty dayes, can you do ſo? and thus people would fain ſlip their necks out of the nooze: for I would ask them, wherefore was Chriſt humble and meek? why did he pray, and watch, and weep? why was he patient, and courteous to all, but onely for our example, that we ſhould imitate him; and ſhall we not ſtrive to do any of theſe vertues, but ſlight them all, becauſe we cannot do them with that perfection as Chriſt did them, is not this meer madneſs to think? but
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152613:58"/>let ſuch people know, that as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the beſt of us to do them with exactneſs, as he did, ſo God doth not require it from us; but to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of our powers we are bound to practiſe them, and ſo we are this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian act of faſting; the force and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of which,<note place="margin">Mat. 17. v. 21.</note> as our Saviour ſaith, Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out ſome ſorts of Devils; which being ſo, we may very well think that God cannot but be pleaſed with the doing of it; and we may juſtly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the Apoſtles were ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of this rule: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his counſel that he gave to <hi>Timothy,</hi> bids him to mingle a little wine with his water for his healths ſake:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. v. 23.</note> which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhows, that he chiefly abſtain'd from ſtrong drink, drinking onely water: and ſo it is ſaid of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> that his meat was locuſts and wilde honey; which was very hard food for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body in any delights, but rather ſerved as they deſigned them, for mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification; and that is the onely cauſe that Gods Church commands her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to faſt and abſtain from meat that they may in ſome meaſure break their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152613:58"/>own wills, and mortifie their fleſhly members, that they may be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to Gods will, and better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to his holy ſervice. It would be too tedious to ſet down all places of holy Scripture to prove this, as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten faſting of the Iſraelites, and of King <hi>David,</hi> who mourned, and wept,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. v. 12.</note> and faſted until evening: and of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> that mourned and faſted certain dayes,<note place="margin">Nehem. 1. v. 4.</note> and prayed before the God of heaven; and in another place the Jews faſted and prayed with earth upon their heads:<note place="margin">Ch. 9. v. 1.</note> and as it was a practiſe by all our fore-fathers, ſo it is, and ever will be in Gods Church. Again, we read that all the City of <hi>Nineveh</hi> at the preaching of <hi>Jonas</hi> put on ſack-cloth,<note place="margin">Jonah 3. v. 7.</note> and faſted, both man and beaſt: now in my opinion theſe proofs might have been omitted, for the proof of this point, ſince reaſon and Chriſtianity might induce us to practice that which in it ſelf is the occaſion of much good, both for ſoul and body: It hath been ſo general a practice in all ages by Gods Church, that Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">They were guilty of a mortal ſin that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152613:59"/>did not ſaft the holy time of Lent;</q> and certainly there is none that is thus ſick of that diſeaſe, but thoſe, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wholly upon kitching phyſick, and ſo take ſo much care to preſerve and feed the body that they totally neglect the medicines and food for the ſoul. And beſides, what hath been ſaid as to the example of Chriſt, and the good it procures to our ſouls, let us conſider what holy intents the Catholick Church hath in the keepign of ſome particular dayes of faſting, and as for the time of Lent, ſhe hath ordained the keeping of it forty dayes before the Paſſion and Reſurrection of our Saviour; firſt, to imitate to the utmoſt of our power, his holy example. Secondly, that we ſhould by Faſting and Praying then, more then ordinary, have a dolorous reſentment of his bitter Paſſion, which he ſuffered for us. And thirdly, that we might with true prepared hearts ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the happy time of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of his glorious body, and with reverence approach to the holy Sacraments of Gods Church; and for our Faſting on Friday every week, it is
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152613:59"/>that we may all ceaſe from the pleaſures of our taſte, that day our Saviour ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Gall and Vinegar; and a little to puniſh our bodies by faſting, when our Saviour ſuffered ſo many dolorous wounds for us, in his tender and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Body, for the ſalvation of the world. Now if any one can finde any evil in theſe intents and practices of the Church, let them quarrel with them ſtill; but if not (as I am ſure juſtly they cannot) then are they bound in conſcience to follow the practice of ſo holy an Inſtitution. I will a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs from my firſt purpoſe, by quoting an ancient Father or two for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this point, and ſo conclude this Chapter; as firſt, St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſaith he) by faſting forty dayes were filled with a familiarity with God;<note place="margin">In c. 58. Iſa.</note> and our Lord himſelf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted as many in the Wilderneſs, to leave unto us the ſolemn dayes of Faſt, that is Lent.</q> And again (ſaith he) <q rend="margQuotes">We faſt forty dayes,<note place="margin">Ep. <hi>54.</hi> ad Marcel.</note> or make one Lent in a year, according to the Traditions of the Apoſtles, in time convenient:</q> And grave St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:152613:60"/>ſaith plainly, <q rend="margQuotes">That it was not ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by men, but conſecrated by God, nor invented by any earthly cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but commanded by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Majeſty:</q> thus is it plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that this practice is no new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but what hath been generally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by all holy men who have been Members of the Roman Catholick Church, and ſo will it continue, as long as God hath a Church upon earth, which we are ſure will be until the conſummation of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Proving that Scripture is very hard to be underſtood, and that we cannot right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know the meaning of it, but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying upon the Church of God, which is infallible; contrary to Proteſtants Opinion.</head>
               <p>IT would not ſeem a little ſtrange, did we but conſider the folly of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men who have ſuch low thoughts of Angels and Saints, as that they know
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152613:60"/>nothing; and yet are ſo groſly arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant of their own knowledge, that none of the grand Myſteries of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (as they think) are unknown to them, and that the whole Church of God is leſs to be truſted in then they; and ſo by this demy Devil, ſelf-conceit, they wrong themſelves, and ſtrive to deprive Gods Church of that privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which Chriſt hath given to her alone, with commands to us, to hear and obey her in all things concerning our Salvation: but had theſe men been acquainted with St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> he would have told them another ſtory, who cryes out concerning Scripture, <q rend="margQuotes">O wonderful profoundneſs of thy words, wonderful profoundneſs, my God, wonderful profoundneſs, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man quake to look on it, to quake for reverence, and to tremble for the love of it; and thoſe places (ſaith he) which I know not, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more then thoſe that I know:</q> by which every conſiderate man may judge with himſelf, that if this great Doctor and light of Gods Church had this opinion of Scripture, and of his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152613:61"/>weakneſs in expounding it, what little reaſon every particular man hath to think it eaſie for him to do, that never was ſo learned, and inſpired of God as he was, as all the Chriſtian world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and that his opinion then, is agreeable to the Catholick Church now; and that to Gods holy word, ſhall be made moſt manifeſt; and firſt from St. <hi>Peters</hi> own teſtimony, who though he was an Apoſtle of Chriſt, yet apprehended Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles to be very hard in the underſtanding of them: as alſo in all his Epiſtles (ſaith he) are many things hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, unto their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And if there be ſo many places hard to be underſtood, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may be juſtly conclude there is in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> where, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith, every ſentence is a Myſtery; and how many in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and in the Propheſies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and many other places; and I would know how any particular man can tell what Chriſt meant in many Myſteries he ſpake, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152613:61"/>how he knows what the Angel meant when he revealed thoſe high Myſteries to St. <hi>John,</hi> and what <hi>Solomon</hi> meant when he declared theſe excellent ſimidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Gods Church, and what St. <hi>Paul</hi> meant when he writ thoſe hard places ſpoken of: if they anſwer me, Gods Spirit tells them the meaning, and that they are perſwaded 'tis ſo, let every one judge how poor this anſwer is (which is common amongſt them) for cannot every Sectary plead the ſame; a Cobler may alledge that as well as a Doctor, and a Tinker as well as a Divine: and this preſumption of interpreting the Bible by private ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, hath been the cauſe of all theſe Sects and Opinions that are now in the world, which would rend the ſeam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Coat of Chriſt, which is his Church, in pieces if they could. If God had ordered every one to be his own Interpreter, he would never have cauſed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us to obey our Paſtours whom he hath placed to rule over us: and (ſaith he) <hi>Submit your ſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
                  <hi>for they watch for your ſols, and ſhall give an account for
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152613:62"/>you.</hi> It is a wonder that this Text i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not blotted out by all ſelf-conceite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people, or that they do not deny it to be good Scripture (as they do many other places) for if, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith here, we muſt obey our Paſtours, (that is thoſe that teach the true Faith of Gods Church) why then we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our own fancies in expounding hard places of Scripture, becauſe God hath given it in their charge to do that, and put us into their charge too to be guided by them; for ſaith the Text, <hi>Submit to them,</hi> and how do we that when we ſcorn them, and ſubmit to none but our own will, quite contrary to Gods holy word, which one day will be the onely witneſs againſt ſuch kinde of men: and ſince Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that they watch over our ſouls, and ſhall give an account for us; who is it but thoſe that are blinde, doth not ſee that we are bound in conſcience to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their judgements. But the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peeviſh objection by many people is, ſhall I pin my faith upon any mans ſleeve, or cannot I know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Bible my ſelf, it is plain
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152613:62"/>enough: and thus poor ſouls are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably cheated by the ſubtilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, for this ſnare catches thouſands; for it is the very ſame that caught our firſt Parents; for he made them believe that they ſhould be as wiſe as God,<note place="margin">Gen. 3. ver. 5.</note> to know good and evil; and ſo he leads theſe kinde of men to their deſruction, by telling them they may be as wiſe as their Paſtors, if they read the Bible they ſhall know the meaning as well as they: and ſo theſe helliſh ſuggeſtions paſſeth currant with them, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that telleth them the meaning of all; for the Devil well knoweth, that if he poſſeſſeth any with ſelf-conceit, he has done his work: And now I have diſcovered this great abuſe that is put upon many men, I will proſecute the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and declare what we is beſt to be taken, to know thoſe hard places in Scripture, and the true ſenſe of them; Firſt, we are to renounce our own judgements, which may eaſily deceive us, and reſign our ſelves to Gods Church which cannot; for ſince we are ſure that God ever had in the world a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, and that this Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152613:63"/>not erre, as I have proved before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Ghoſt is the guider of it; what better way can any man poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly deviſe, then by ſubmitting his Faith to Gods Church, for if we do ſo we do what God commands us, and then we diſcharge our duty; which if they that are in the viſible Government of it teach us any thing that they ought not to do, they ſhall anſwer it it to God, and not we, for we are in their charge, and they muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for us, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> before tell us; and let any man in reaſon judge, (if there were no command for it by God) whether it be not more ſecure to ſtand to the uniform judgement of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand grave Doctors in Gods Church, which all agree in one expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Bible now, and with all that hath gone before, that were of the ſame Church, then with their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpirit, or to relye upon thoſe that cannot agree amongſt themſelves, but ar ein continual conteſt one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. And for our further aſſurance and ſecurity we ſhall have, by reſigning our ſelves to the Church, we are to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152613:63"/>conſider, that as Gods Church is guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his power from the Gates of Hell ever having any power over it, ſo we as Members of it can never fall from our Faith, as long as we are ſo reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for till then we are continually wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and unconſtant in our mindes, as too many by experience findes it true; but when we are ſo ſettled we have perfect freedom to ſerve God, in that ſecond principle of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is good works. I ſhall onely add one thing to all ſerious peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, that is, why there is ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of Bibles amongſt Proteſtants, and all Sectaries, and what their deſign is in it: as for example, ſome have all the Books of Scripture, and ſome leave out the Apocraphy (as they call it) ſome have Contents to their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters, and ſome have not, and every tranſlation differs in a thouſand places at the leaſt; and the reaſon of it is clear to thoſe that are not willing to be cheated in their ſouls, becauſe every Tranſlator makes them dance after his Pipe; that is, the Bible he tranſlates, ſhall be ſure to favour his pernicious
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152613:64"/>opinions; and being taxed with it, they all cry, the meaning is the ſame: but I would demand of thoſe preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, how they dare to alter the Scripture, either by adding or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, ſince there is a curſe pronounced againſt them that do,<note place="margin">Rev. 22. v. 18, 19.</note> by God himſelf: for ſince we are all ſurek, that the firſt Bible that we had for our inſtruction,<note place="margin">Deut. 4. v. 2.</note> was writ by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt; is it not a high preſumption for any man to vary from that, and then pretend that the meaning is the ſame, when many times the altering of one Letter mars the ſenſe of a whole Sentence; much more when they alter a word, nay Sentences themſelves, to work their own deſigns; as if, what God ordained at firſt had need to be corrected by their wiſdoms: by which it doth appear, that if every Heretick could have his will, he would truſt out of Scripture all places that make againſt his principles; and yet it would (with them) be as good Scripture as any: and then to interpret that by their own private ſpirits, muſt needs bring ſtrange confuſion, both in the knowing which
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152613:64"/>is the true word of God, and what the meaning of it is. If we conſult with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David</hi> we ſhall finde that he appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended more difficulty in knowing the word of God then theſe kinde of men do; who ſaith, <hi>Give me underſtanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. v. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>O God, and I will ſearch thy Law:</hi> ſure he was as wiſe as any that pretend ſo much of the Spirit, and yet he would not ſo much as ſearch into thoſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries without particular aſſiſtance from God. So we read that the <hi>Eunuch</hi> which was a man of great authority un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Queen of <hi>Candice,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of great knowledge; yet when Saint <hi>Philip</hi> the Apoſtle asked him whether he underſtood what he read out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> concerning Chriſt, he anſwered, <hi>How can I,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8.30, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>except ſome man ſhould guide me?</hi> and then <hi>Philip</hi> (whoſe charge it was) declared the meaning to him; by which we may ſee that he, though a great man, was not ſo preſumptuous to interpret Scripture of himſelf, as many do now; and yet might as well have pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſpirit as they: ſince we ſee, he was ſo well given, as to go ſo far
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152613:65"/>from his own Countrey to worſhip God in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to read the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his going home. In like manner our Saviour meeting with two of his Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 24. v. 27, 45.</note> after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, it is ſaid he expounded to them all the Scriptures; and when they were altogether he appeared to them, and opened their underſtandings, that they might know the Scriptures: from whence we may juſtly gather, that if his Diſciples and Apoſtles (which were ſo converſant with Chriſt in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time) were ſo ignorant of Scripture, as not to know the meaning of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which foretold his Reſurrection, the third day, and other Myſteries of his Death and ſufferings, what igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance then have we (or at leaſt we ought to think ſo) that never had thoſe large means that the Apoſtles had: but ſuch is the miſerable ſtate of theſe unhappy times, that many think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more wiſe, and more holy, then the Apoſtles were, or then the whole Church of God is now; and I think in time they will like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſuppoſe themſelves equal to God himſelf. Thus
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152613:65"/>having ſufficiently proved the difficulty of underſtanding the Scripture, with the danger of expounding it, to our own private ſenſe; together with what courſe to follow in knowing the true meaning, which is by adhering to Gods holy Church: I will conclude with that ſaying of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtin. l. <hi>1.</hi> cont. Creſcon.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Then do we hold (ſaith he) the verity of the Scriptures, when we do that which now ſeemeth good to the Univerſal Church, which the authority of Scripture themſelves do commend; ſo that foraſmuch as the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture cannot deceive, whoſoever then is afraid to be deceived with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity of queſtions, let him therein ask counſel of the ſame Church, which the holy Scripture moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and evidently pointeth and ſheweth unto us.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:152613:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> Proving the neceſſity of the Churches Divine Servince to be ſaid in the Latine Tongue, or in one Language, in all places of the world where it is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; contrary to Proteſtants Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</head>
               <p>DId all Chriſtians follows the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of our Bleſſed Saviour in his commanding us to ſubmit and adhere to Gods Church, there would not be ſuch quarrellings in our mindes, nor bad ſpeeches from our mouths, againſt her holy Inſtitutions; which though ſometimes have not an apparent riſe from Scripture, yet are ordained in the Church by the inſtinct of the Holy Ghoſt; who (as I ſaid) is alwayes with her to direct her in all her propoſals to us concerning our Salvation: and as we may reaſonably think, that as God hath committed to her charge the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the holy Sacraments to us, and other high qualities, ſo he hath inveſted her with power to Ordain,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152613:66"/>Conſtitute, and Decree, any thing that may be to the good and benefit of the ſame Church; which Decrees and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions we are bound to obſerve, and without any difficulty in Conſcience may, ſo long as it is not againſt Gods word, but rather agreeable to the ſame: amongſt which things that are thus conſtituted by the Church, this of the Latine Service is one, which I ſhall prove to be ſomewhat agreeable to Scripture, and altogether to Reaſon, and the practice of the Church of God in all Ages. Firſt, we will obſerve ſomething pertinent to this in Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel, wheere he declares,<note place="margin">Luke 1. v. 10.</note> that when <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Prieſt was offering and praying to God in the Temple, for himſelf and all the people, that the whole multitude of the people were praying without at the time of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Incenſe; by which it appears, that they knew not what he ſaid, nor underſtood any thing of it; which is now the main objection againſt us in this point by our Adverſaries: but to ſatisfie theſe people, we are to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that the publick or common Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152613:67"/>of Gods Church, being compos'd of Sucrifice, Prayers, and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, is therefore chiefly deſigned for the honour and glory of God, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day offered up to him by the Prieſts, and not for the edification of the people; ſo much by underſtanding it, as by the benefit they receive and partake of, being preſent at it; for when the Prieſt ſaith the ſervice of the Church he offers it to God for himſelf,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14 v. 2. Heb 5. v. 1.2, 3.</note> for the people preſent, for the whole Church, or for any other neceſſities of people that are abſent; ſo that it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not whether they underſtand him or no, ſince they have as much benefit of his Prayers as if they did; for if they heard him not ſpeak a word it were the ſame thing, ſo long as God both hears him and underſtands him, to whom it is offered and deſigned; for in Sacrifice, Prayer, and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, the Prieſts ſpak to God, and not to the people: for example, when any man lies ſick, or in diſtreſs at home, he ſends to the Church to be prayed for, by the Miniſter and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, now ſhall we think becauſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152613:67"/>he hears nor underſtands not thoſe which pray for him, that he hath no benefit by their prayers, this were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to think; for then we ſhould be never the better for our Saviours Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to his heavenly Father for us, whom we underſtand not, nor know when, nor for what he intercedes to him, and yet we all receive much good by it; and ſo we do in the Prieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Service, who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the place of our Saviour on earth to mediate for us; and we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that the effectual ſervent prayers of a righteous man prevaileth much,<note place="margin">James 5. v. 16.</note> whether we hear and underſtand them or no: but yet to diſcover the folly of thoſe that impugne this practiſe, they may pleaſe to take notice, that the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tongue is not ſo much unknown or underſtood, as it is thought it is; for if there was any need to underſtand the Service (as I have proved there is not) there be many thouſands of our Church and others that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Latine Tongue, and thoſe people that do not, are ſo well inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Church, that with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152613:68"/>and the cuſtom of hearing Maſs, they know when to kneel, and when to ſtand, when to pray, and when to give thanks; when to do reverence, and when not: beſides moſt of the Service they have in their Engliſh Books, and may know any part of the reſt when they will, if there were any need, as there is none; ſo that it is not ſaid in Latine becauſe the common people ſhould not underſtand it, (as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks falſly report) but for a great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and convenience in the Church (as I ſhall ſuddenly prove:) but firſt it is obſervable, that though the common people in <hi>England</hi> read th Bible in Engliſh, yet they underſtand not half of it; nor which is worſe, are never made to underſtand it; yet Proteſtants will ſay they muſt not therefore leave the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it quite, becauſe the underſtanding of ſome parts is beneficial to them; ſo their Common Prayer being read and ſung in Cathedrals and other places, is not underſtood by many of the wiſer ſort, much leſs by the common people, and ſo is all one, as if it were in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; yet if there were any benefit to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152613:68"/>be had, it would be never the leſs to them, becauſe they underſtood it not; ſince as I ſaid before, it is offered to God onely for all the Church, and not to us. And ſince it is ſo in theſe practices amongſt them, I hope they will not but think that thoſe that are ignorant amongſt us, may, and do receive much comfort by our Churches Service; ſince by being ſo often at it, and good inſtructions from Prieſts, they come in ſhort time to the knowledge and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: but perhaps ſome may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that ſince we cannot underſtand them perfectly, why ſhould we go to Church to hear the Servince? to which I anſer, that it is without complare bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to go to Gods Church to offer our Devotions by every ones praying to God, by being preſent at the Inſtitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Bleſſed Sacrament, by ſeeing devout people receive it, with true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: beſides, none but Atheiſts will deny, but that it is better to do any act of Devotion in a Church dedicated to Gods holy Service and nothing elſe, then in a prophane houſe, which is chiefly deſigned for temporal buſineſs:
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152613:69"/>but indeed, as Proteſtants do their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in Churches, there is no great difference, who ſit on their tails, ſtaring about them when their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer is ſaid, and have more regard to the manner, then to the matter performed. But it is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with Catholicks in the Church, for there every one is on their knees, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for ſuch things as they ſtand in need of, and the Prieſt prayes for them all; ſo that were it in the Mother Tongue it ſignified nothing more, and if they heard him not ſpeak a word it were the ſame: for why? the Prieſt is bound to ſay the Divine Service every day, if there were no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preſent but himſelf; and yet we may receive benefit by his Prayers too, that neither ſee, hear, nor underſtand him, becauſe the prayers of any good man prevailes with God, though the perſons prayed for were a thouſand miles off. This now that hath been ſaid may ſuffice any moderate perſon, as to the belief that there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of underſtanding the Common Service (as there is in the hearing of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152613:69"/>Sermons, for thoſe are alwayes preached in the Mother Tongue to common people) becauſe when the Prieſt ſaith Maſs, or Divine Service, he ſpeaks to God, and when they preach, it is directed to man onely. But now I will ſhow the reaſon why it is ſaid in Latine in all places of the world, and the convenience of it: Firſt, we are to conſider that the Catholickd Church is not pinn'd up into one Kingdom, or Dominion, as other Churches are, that ſay their Service in the Mother tongue; for which reaſon, ſince that all Nations from her receive one uniform Faith, ſo they have all one Service, in one Language, which hath many conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences with it (and no incommodity at all) for by that maeans Prieſts that are ſent into Forreign Countreyes, where they ſpeak never a word of the Language when they come there, yet may do that for which they were ſent and commanded there; that is, ſay Maſs and adminiſter the Sacraments, as well as if they did, and thoſe in thoſe Countreyes where they are ſent, can as well underſtand them as their
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152613:70"/>own Prieſts they had before, being Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives: Beſides many thouſands of Catholicks travel from one part of Chriſtendome to another, and come where they will in any of their Churches, they underſtand and hear the ſame Service that they do at home; which if it were not ſaid in all places in one Language they could not; for ſince the Catholick Church is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſo many Nations, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually travelling and mixing one with the other, it would be barbarious to all ſtrangers to hear that Service which none of them underſtood: (If there were any neceſſity for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it) as for example, the French, Spaniards, Italians, Dutch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> come all at one time to our Service, here in <hi>England;</hi> now were it ſaid in Engliſh, it would be barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to them all; but being in the ſame Tongue, as it is in their own Countreyes, they underſtand it as well as if they were there: ſo that the diſcreet Reader may ſee what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and convenience the Church hath in uſing the Latine ſervice; which
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152613:70"/>if it were confined to ſo narrow limits as others are, would uſe none but the Mother Tongue as others do: ſo that all Chriſtians may, ſee the integrity of Gods Church, which in this and all other points, orders every thing for the good and convenience of all her Members; &amp; which is done with ſo much wiſdome and prudence, that it plainly appears to be guided by the Spirit of God: as alſo the malice of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is ſhown, who make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Papiſts are kept in groſs ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and muſt not read the Bible, nor muſt not underſtand the Common Service, becauſe they ſhall not (as they ſay) know what the evil of it is: and ſuch fooleries in continually buzzed in their ears, but bow ſlanderouſly let every Chriſtian judge. Now that this hath been the practice of the whole Church for this ſixteen hundred years, and the belief of all the ancient Fathers, our adverſaries themſelves know ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, yet for the love of their large Revenues will not diſcover it (nor other points as true as Goſpel) to the people that want underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152613:71"/>for which one day they muſt be ſure to give a ſevere account to God, whom they cannot deceive. And for to bring in the Sentences of the Fathers to prove this, would ſwell this Book into a larger Volume then is deſigned; I will quote them where they are to be found, that every one may know their practice in this point, (and firſt ſee Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Expo. orat. domn.</hi> 13. Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ep.</hi> 65. <hi>Jerome, Prefat. in Pſal. ad Sophron. Chriſoſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13.) and conclude with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. v. 16.</note> that if after all this that hath been ſaid, <hi>any man be contentious, we have no ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, nor the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152613:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap 17.</hi> Treating in general of both Churches.</head>
               <p>NOw having plainly proved all the chief points of our Faith by the Proteſtants own Bible, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a little to ſpeak in general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning both Religions, that all men may conſider and ſee, by their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Riſe, Practice, and Proceedings, which is the likelieſt to be the Church of God, if it had not been, or were not to be proed by Scripture: for in the firſt place we ſhall finde all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions (but the Roman Catholick) ſo like innocents for Age,<note place="margin">They are all Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Gods Church.</note> that they have not yet left their Cradles, that is, they are rocked up and down by their new opinions, and ſo far from being ſettled, that it is to be feared they never will; for what wiſe man can be ſo much an enemy to truth, as to think Gods Church was not ſpread in the world before <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths time, or <hi>Martin Luthers,</hi> or <hi>John
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152613:72"/>Calvins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The riſe of all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries.</note> who were the firſt bringers in of all Religions, but the Roman, (as every one knows which hath read any thing) and for ſuch men who were known to be leud, and evil li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, to pretend new lights, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries from God, for the alteration of Chriſtian Religion, who ſeeth not, but that it was prepoſterous (as it hath proved) for I would demand, why did our Bleſſed Saviour preach Chriſtian Religion, and ſend his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples to preach the ſame to all Nations in the world, that they might plant true points of Faith, and they did do it, and watered it with their Blood; was this done for nothing, that when theſe pretended Reformers came, they muſt make the world believe, that God would undo all again (what had been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed ſo long in all Chriſtendome) to have new Religions of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſet up; ſure theſe men thought, that either God knew not what he did, when he planted the firſt, or that all people but themſelves were
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152613:72"/>very ſimple, to receive a ſecond Faith from them, of their own invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as plainly appeared ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and doth ſtill; for no ſooner were they ſeverally grown to any authority with ſilly people, but they began to rail and revile one againſt the other juſt as we ſee their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding followers do to this day, (which indeed is proper to all Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Hereticks to do) which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then, and now, of what far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance their doctrine was from plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, who is the God of peace, and hareth contention; as alſo far from being of his Church, ſince there is no ſuch cuſtome (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) and yet we ſee by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience in this Kingdome, how theſe Sects (which are the ſpawn of Hereſie) ſtill grow more and more amongſt us; and in their increaſing are ſtill more monſtrous then at firſt, in their opinions againſt God, and Chriſtian Religion; and yet they ſay (as the firſt of them did) that God hath ſent them to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152613:73"/>convert and purge the world, and bring in new Relgions; and ſo all Hereticks that come after this Age will ſay the like; and ſo it ſeems by them that God will never ſettle any, but have every Age a new Religion. And thus we may ſee what a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous ſea Hereſie is, which tumbles them up and down that follow it, and never are at reſt here, till they imbarque themſelves in the ſecure Ship of the Catholick Church, where God himſelf is the Pilot; from whence thoſe unhappy ſouls that went out (and were the cauſe of theſe prodigious ſtorms) have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſhipwrack on the quick-ſands of their own giddy fancies. Again, let us obſerve further, how monſtrous theſe Hereſies and Factions are, and how deſtructive both to mens ſouls, and to Monarchy, in the Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Bodies: Firſt, we may eaſily perceive what ruine it hath brought to many ſouls,<note place="margin">Their bad practices and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</note> when they are taught to deny all theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Faith, proved in this Book
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152613:73"/>by the word of God, and other high points by ſome of them, as the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, is denyed by Antebaptiſts, and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and too many others, and Baptiſme of Infants: and amongſt them altogether, is practiſed ſuch a furious contempt of Gods word, and all the Sacraments and Divine Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, as never was yet known or heard of in the Chriſtian world before; ſo that ſome people are even diſtracted, and know not where to go for to finde reſt for their ſouls, becauſe ſo many Sects pretend for the truth, and are all falſe; becauſe as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, there is but one Faith, one God, and one Baptiſme; and the Catholick Church is the onely Haven for all thoſe troubled ſpirits (that ſeek for truth) to finde repoſe in. And how deſtructive they are to Civill Government, I need not quote any Authour to prove it, ſince our King and Kingdome at home, as well as others abroad, have felt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152613:74"/>the helliſh hands of Hereſie and faction, in ſuch ſort, that Rebelling againſt our (deceaſed) lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, they did not onely ſpill his Royal Blood, but thouſands of his Subjects, and this under the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Religion too as well as any: but they that ſee not theſe to be ſnares and pits of the Devil, deſerve to fall into them, ſince none but thoſe that are wilfully blinde can be caught in ſuch viſible ginns.</p>
               <p>And now as I have briefly ſhown you the rough and ſtormy Seas of Hereſie and Factions, ſo I will open the gate to let you ſee the ſmooth and pleaſanteſt Waters of Gods Church, which runs through every vein of the world peaceably, without noiſe or diſturbance, agreeable to his Word, wo ſaid, My peace I leave with you, and that you love one another as I have loved you; which words of our Saviour is no where obſerved (as I have ſhown by the malice and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that is amongſt Hereticks) but
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152613:74"/>in the Catholick Church,<note place="margin">The Churches Antiquity and riſe.</note> which hath had this peace which Chriſt left ever ſince he left it; and as it began then in his time, and the Apoſtles, to be a famous Church throughout the world, ſo hath it continued in the ſame ſplendor and purity to this day, as is plainly ſeen; firſt, by her being ſo conformable in her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhe now teacheth, to the true and infallible word of God (as I have proved.) Secondly, in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of her lawful Line of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours. Thirdly, in her Apoſtolical care for the Converſion of Nations, that know not God, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might periſh. Fourthly,<note place="margin">The Churches practice.</note> by her Miracles famed throughout the world, as our Saviour ſaid, who ever did believe truly in him ſhould have power to caſt out Devils,<note place="margin">Mark 16. v. 17, 18.</note> and take up Serpents, and drink poiſon and not hurt them; ſo his Church which hath onely truly believed in him, hath onely had many Members that hath truly done thoſe Miracles (as many Proteſtants themſelves confeſs.) Again,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152613:75"/>if we conſider the different order that is in both Churches, it may juſtly amaze all reaſonable men; the Prieſts of the Catholick Church never marry, nor enjoy any great Eſtates, that ſo they may be freely diveſted from the worlds intereſts (as the Apoſtles were) to attend wholly to perform their charge in Gods Church, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of ſouls; on the contrary, the Miniſters of all other Churches do ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally marry, and enjoy very great Poſſeſſions, and Riches; by which they are ſo incumbred with the world, as very few are more, as we daily ſee by their continual Suits of Law, and griping cares to advance themſelves from one great Benefice to another; not at all conſidering, that if they were true Paſtours, they ſhould feed Gods Sheep; that is, go preach in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote places of the world amongſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans that know not God, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, and as Catholick Prieſts do to this day; and as all muſt do that follow the examples and commands left by Chriſt, or elſe they cannot be
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152613:75"/>of his ſending; by which we have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great reaſon to ſuſpect all theſe new teachers that lie at home at eaſe and pleaſure, and are ſo far from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the toil and pains of converting Pagans,<note place="margin">This is too truly proved by many that dye and never have either Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments nor any other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from them in their ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Death.</note> that many of them will not ſtir to a poor perſon that lies a dying, becauſe they cannot receive a golden Recompence. Again, in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church there be many thouſands of her Members that are Royally and Nobly Born to great Poſſeſſions, that quit them all to ſerve God in ſtrict courſes of Religion; as Faſting, Watching, Praying, giving Almes, and many other bodily Mortifications, in Religious Houſes, where nothing but the Service of God is exalted.<note place="margin">The vaſt difference of the two Churches practice.</note> Now I would fain know from whence the doing of ſo much good doth proceed, but from the inſpiration of God; and for to finde one now of any other Religion, nobly born, or of mean quality, to forſake an Eſtate for the Service of God in their way, would be ſuch a miracle, as was yet never heard of amongſt them, nor never
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152613:76"/>will be: but on the contrary, all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all conditions take their full career in doing what they pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for they will not hear the Church, nor Faſt, nor Pray, nor receive the Sacrament but when their fancy pleaſes, and ſo are let run in a negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſtate never to give an account for their ſinful actions to the Church at all; (as God commands we ſhould) and ſo by tis means the flood-gate of all evil is opened, for all manner of people to plunge themſelves over head ad ears in miſery and utter calamity. I could enlarge my ſelf in ſhowing the vaſt difference in many other practices, as the beauty and ornaments of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Churches, when others are like Barnes in compariſon of them; the Reverence and Devotion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick people in them, who on their knees adore God whilſt others ſit at eaſe, ſome gazing, and ſome aſleep, with many other practices of the like kinde: but this may, and will ſuffice (for all thoſe that deſire to entertain truth, and to minde the ſalvation of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152613:76"/>their ſouls) to ſhow clearly which is Gods Church, and which is not; ſo that which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold is here made good, that the Church of God ſhould be a plain way, and a direct way, ſo that fools could not erre therein; ſo that all thoſe that itnend at the laſt day to be ſeparated from the goats, muſt now in this life graze with Gods Sheep; that is, they muſt enter into communion with his Catholick Church, whereof Chriſt Jeſus is the Head.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:152613:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152613:77"/>
            <head>The Conents of the Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Chapter 1.</label>
               <item>Proving the Bleſſed Sacrament. <hi>page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 2.</label>
               <item>Proving Confeſſion to a Prieſt. <hi>page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 3.</label>
               <item>Proving Purgatory. <hi>page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 4.</label>
               <item>Proving that none went to Heaven before Chriſt dyed. <hi>page 25</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 5.</label>
               <item>Proving that Angels and Saints know our actions on earth. <hi>page 31</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152613:78"/>
               <label>Chap. 6.</label>
               <item>Proving it lawful to pray to them. <hi>page 39</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 7.</label>
               <item>Proving it lawful to worſhip them. <hi>page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 8.</label>
               <item>Proving the lawfulneſs of Images. <hi>page 59</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 9.</label>
               <item>Proving Free-will in Man to do good. <hi>page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 10.</label>
               <item>Proving Good Works to be Meritorious. <hi>page 76</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 11.</label>
               <item>Proving that Gods Church cannot Erre. <hi>page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 12.</label>
               <item>Proving the Churches Authority in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins. <hi>page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 13.</label>
               <item>Proving the Churches <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality. <hi>page 98</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 14.</label>
               <item>Proving the lawfulneſſe of Faſting. <hi>page 108</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152613:78"/>
               <label>Chap. 15.</label>
               <item>Proving the difficulty of underſtanding Scripture. <hi>page 114</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 16.</label>
               <item>Proving the neceſſity of the Churches Service in one Tongue, in all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. <hi>page 126</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chap. 17.</label>
               <item>Shewing in general the vaſt difference of both Churches. <hi>page 137</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
